<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Java Python on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/java-python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Java Python on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 14:24:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/java-python/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>From Double Precision Normal Density to Double Precision Cumulative Normal Distribution</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/from-double-precision-normal-density-to-double-precision-cumulative-normal-distribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 14:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/from-double-precision-normal-density-to-double-precision-cumulative-normal-distribution/</guid>
      <description>Marsaglia in his paper on Normal Distribution made the same mistake I initially did while trying to verify the accuracy of the normal density.
In his table of values comparing the true value computed by Maple for some values of x to the values computed by Sun or Ooura erfc, he actually does not really use the same input for the comparison. One example is the last number: 16.6. 16.6 does not have an exact representation in double precision, even though it is displayed as 16. <a href="/post/from-double-precision-normal-density-to-double-precision-cumulative-normal-distribution/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying Google AppEngine</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/trying-google-appengine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2008 19:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/trying-google-appengine/</guid>
      <description>I finally took some time to try Google AppEngine. It used to be easy to find free PHP hosting around 2000. It became a rarity. So writing small experiments for free on the web was difficult. Experiments are back thanks to Google with their AppEngine. Many aspects of it are quite interesting and show where they focus.
First it is all Python. It makes sense as I believe Guido v Rossum, Python creator, works for Google. <a href="/post/trying-google-appengine/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
