<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quant on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/categories/quant/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Quant on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 23:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/quant/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogs on Quantitative Finance</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/typo-in-hyman-non-negative-constraint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/typo-in-hyman-non-negative-constraint/</guid>
      <description>There are not many blogs on quantitative finance that I read. Blogs are not so popular anymore with the advent of the various social networks (facebook, stackoverflow, google plus, reddit, &amp;hellip;). Here is a small list:
 Clarus FT: often interesting statistics on the swap market, clearing, plus the more technical articles from Gary. Quants R Us: A relatively new blog with a promising starting post analyzing Andreasen-Huge one-step local-volatility algorithm with a Spline Fooling around with Quantlib: the blog from Peter Caspers, also relevant to non-Quantlib professionals has original insights such as Smile dynamics by densities or the Supernatural Libor Coupons. <a href="/post/typo-in-hyman-non-negative-constraint/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implied Volatility from Black-Scholes price</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implied-volatility-from-black-scholes-price/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implied-volatility-from-black-scholes-price/</guid>
      <description>Dan Stefanica and Rados Radoicic propose a quite good initial guess in their very recent paper An Explicit Implied Volatility Formula. Their formula is simple, fast to compute and results in an implied volatility guess with a relative error of less than 10%.
It is more robust than the rational fraction from Minquiang Li: his rational fraction is only valid for a fixed range of strikes and maturities. The new approximation is mathematically proved accurate across all strikes and all maturities. <a href="/post/implied-volatility-from-black-scholes-price/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The VIX starts smiling</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/vix-starts-smiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/vix-starts-smiling/</guid>
      <description>The VIX implied volatilities used to look like a logarithmic function of the strikes. I don&amp;rsquo;t look at them often, but today, I noticed that the VIX had the start of a smile shape.
 1m VIX implied volatilities on March 21, 2017 with strictly positive volume.   Very few strikes trades below the VIX future level (12.9). All of this is likely because the VIX is unusually low: not many people are looking to trade it much lower. <a href="/post/vix-starts-smiling/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When SVI Breaks Down</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/when-svi-breaks-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/when-svi-breaks-down/</guid>
      <description>In order to fit the implied volatility smile of equity options, one of the most popular parameterization is Jim Gatheral&amp;rsquo;s SVI, which I have written about before here.
It turns out that in the current market conditions, SVI does not work well for short maturities. SPX options expiring on March 24, 2017 (one week) offer a good example. I paid attention to include only options with non zero volume, that is options that are actually traded. <a href="/post/when-svi-breaks-down/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brownian Bridge and Discrete Random Variables</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 14:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/</guid>
      <description>The new Heston discretisation scheme I wrote about a few weeks ago makes use a discrete random variable matching the first five moments of the normal distribution instead of the usual normally distributed random variable, computed via the inverse cumulative distribution function. Their discrete random variable is: $$\xi = \sqrt{1-\frac{\sqrt{6}}{3}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 &amp;lt; 3\,,$$ $$ \xi =-\sqrt{1-\frac{\sqrt{6}}{3}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 &amp;gt; 4\,,$$ $$\xi = \sqrt{1+\sqrt{6}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 = 3\,,$$ $$\xi = -\sqrt{1+\sqrt{6}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 = 4\,,$$ with \(U_1 \in \{0,1,&amp;hellip;,7\}\) <a href="/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new scheme for Heston - Part 2</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 07:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/</guid>
      <description>A couple weeks ago, I wrote about a new Heston discretisation scheme which was at least as accurate as Andersen QE scheme and faster, called DVSS2.
It turns out that it does not behave very well on the following Vanilla forward start option example (which is quite benign). The Heston parameters comes from a calibration to the market and are
$$v_0= 0.0718, \kappa= 1.542, \theta= 0.0762, \sigma= 0.582, \rho= -0. <a href="/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence between floating-strike and fixed-strike Asian options</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/</guid>
      <description>Many papers present formulae to price Asian options in the Black-Scholes world only for the fixed strike Asian case, that is a contract that pays \( \max(A-K,0)\) at maturity \(T\) where \(A = \sum_{i=0}^{n-1} w_i S(t_i) \) is the Asian average.
More generally, this can be seen as the payoff of a Basket option where the underlyings are just the same asset but at different times. And any Basket option formula can actually be used to price fixed-strike Asian options by letting the correlation correspond to the correlation between the asset at the averaging times and the variances correspond to the variance at each averaging time. <a href="/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelier Normal Volatility Asymptotics</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/</guid>
      <description>It is relatively well known that the Black-Scholes volatility can not grow faster than \(\sqrt{\ln(K)}\). The rule is also sometimes simply stated as &amp;ldquo;the implied variance can not grow faster than linear&amp;rdquo; (in log-moneyness). The proof comes from Roger Lee &amp;ldquo;The moment formula for implied volatility at extreme strikes&amp;rdquo; but the rule was suggested earlier, for example in Hodge&amp;rsquo;s paper from 1996 &amp;ldquo;Arbitrage bounds of the implied volatility strike and term structures of European-style options&amp;rdquo;. <a href="/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new scheme for Heston</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 07:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled recently upon a new Heston discretisation scheme, in the spirit of Alfonsi, not more complex and more accurate.
My first attempt at coding the scheme resulted in a miserable failure even though the described algorithm looked not too difficult. I started wondering if the paper, from a little known Lithuanian mathematical journal, was any good. Still, the math in it is very well written, with a great emphasis on the settings for each proposition. <a href="/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Andreasen-Huge interpolation - Don&#39;t stay flat</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/</guid>
      <description>Jesper Andreasen and Brian Huge propose an arbitrage-free interpolation method based on a single-step forward Dupire PDE solution in their paper Volatility interpolation. To do so, they consider a piecewise constant representation of the local volatility in maturity time and strike where the number of constants matches the number of market option prices.
An interesting example that shows some limits to the technique as described in Jesper Andreasen and Brian Huge paper comes from Nabil Kahale paper on an arbitrage-free interpolation of volatilities. <a href="/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
