<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>quant on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/categories/quant/</link>
    <description>Recent content in quant on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 07:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/categories/quant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Remarkable Coincidences, Bad Book?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/reghai_remarkable_coincidences/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/reghai_remarkable_coincidences/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon a new short book Financial Models in Production from O. Kettani and A. Reghai. A page attracted my attention
 A page from Kettani and Reghai&amp;#39;s book.   This is the same example as I used on my blog, where I also present the Li&amp;rsquo;s SOR method combined with the good initial guess from Stefanica. The idea has also been expanded on in Jherek Healy&amp;rsquo;s book. What is shocking is that, beside reusing my example, they reuse my timing for Jäckel and my implementation is in Google Go, with a timing done on some older laptop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More on random number generators</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/more-on-random-number-generators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/more-on-random-number-generators/</guid>
      <description>My previous post described the recent view on random number generators, with a focus on the Mersenne-Twister war.
Since, I have noticed another front in the war of the random number generators:
 An example in dimension 121 from K Savvidy where L&amp;rsquo;Ecuyer MRG32k3a fails to compute the correct result, regardless of the seed. This is a manufactured example, such that the vector, used in the example, falls in the dual lattice of the generator.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The war of the random number generators</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/war-of-the-random-number-generators/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2020 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/war-of-the-random-number-generators/</guid>
      <description>These days, there seems to be some sort of small war to define what is a modern good random number generators to advise for simulations. Historically, the Mersenne-Twister (MT thereafter) won this war. It is used by default in many scientific libraries and software, even if there has been a few issues with it:
 A bad initial seed may make it generate a sequence of low quality for at least as many as 700K numbers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sobol with 64-bits integers</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/sobol-64-bits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/sobol-64-bits/</guid>
      <description>A while ago, I wondered how to make some implementation of Sobol support 64-bits integers (long) and double floating points. Sobol is the most used quasi random number generator (QRNG) for (quasi) Monte-Carlo simulations.
The standard Sobol algorithms are all coded with 32-bits integers and lead to double floating point numbers which can not be smaller than \( 2^{-31} \). I was recently looking back at the internals at Sobol generators, and noticed that generating with 64-bits integers would not help much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March 9, 2020 crash - where will CAC40 go?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/mar9-cac40-crash/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 21:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/mar9-cac40-crash/</guid>
      <description>The stock market crashed by more than 7% on March 9, 2020. It is one of the most important drop since September 2001. I looked at BNP warrant prices on the CAC40 French index, with a maturity of March 20, 2020 , to see what they would tell about the market direction on the day of the crash. This is really a not-so-scientific experiment.
The quotes I got were quite noisy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numba, Pypy Overrated?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/python-numba-overrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/python-numba-overrated/</guid>
      <description>Many benchmarks show impressive performance gains with the use of Numba or Pypy. Numba allows to compile just-in-time some specific methods, while Pypy takes the approach of compiling/optimizing the full python program: you use it just like the standard python runtime. From those benchmarks, I imagined that those tools would improve my 2D Heston PDE solver performance easily. The initialization part of my program contains embedded for loops over several 10Ks elements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing NaNs in Quadprog</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quadprog-nans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quadprog-nans/</guid>
      <description>Out of curiosity, I tried quadprog as open-source quadratic programming convex optimizer, as it is looks fast, and the code stays relatively simple. I however stumbled on cases where the algorithm would return NaNs even though my inputs seemed straighforward. Other libraries such as CVXOPT did not have any issues with those inputs.
Searching on the web, I found that I was not the only one to stumble on this kind of issue with quadprog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Probability of a Netflix Stock Crash</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/nflx-stock-crash-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/nflx-stock-crash-probability/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow up to my previous post where I explore the probability of a TSLA stock crash, reproducing the results of Timothy Klassen.
According to the implied cumulative probability density, TSLA has around 15% chance of crashing below $100. Is this really high compared to other stocks? or is it the interpretation of the data erroneous?
Here I take a look at NFLX (Netflix). Below is the implied volatility according to three different models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Probability of a TSLA Stock Crash</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/tsla-stock-crash-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/tsla-stock-crash-probability/</guid>
      <description>Timothy Klassen had an interesting post on linkedin recently, with the title &amp;ldquo;the options market thinks there is a 16% chance that Tesla will not exist in January 2020&amp;rdquo;. As I was also recently looking at the TSLA options, I was a bit intrigued. I looked at the option chain on July 10th, and implied the European volatility from the American option prices. I then fit a few of my favorite models: Andreasen-Huge with Tikhonov regularization, the lognormal mixture, and a polynomial collocation of degree 7.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fourth Moment of the Normal SABR Model</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal-sabr-fourth-moment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal-sabr-fourth-moment/</guid>
      <description>I was wondering if I could use the SABR moments to calibrate a model to SABR parameters directly. It turns out that the SABR moments have relatively simple expressions when \(\beta=0\), that is, for the normal SABR model (with no absorption). This is for the pure SABR stochatic volatility model, not the Hagan approximation. For the Hagan approximation, we would need to use the replication by vanilla options to compute the moments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implying the Probability Density from Market Option Prices (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow-up to my posts on the implied risk-neutral density (RND) of the SPW options before and after the big volatility change that happened in early February with two different techniques: a smoothing spline on the implied volatilities and a Gaussian kernel approach.
The Gaussian kernel (as well as to some extent the smoothing spline) let us believe that there are multiple modes in the distribution (multiple peaks in the density).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implying the Probability Density from Market Option Prices</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I showed a plot of the probability implied from SPW options before and after the big volatility change of last week. I created it from a least squares spline fit of the market mid implied volatilities (weighted by the inverse of the bid-ask spread). While it looks reasonable, the underlying technique is not very robust. It is particularly sensitive to the number of options strikes used as spline nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where is the S&amp;P 500 going to end?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spx500_bets_after_rates_hike/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 19:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spx500_bets_after_rates_hike/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday the American stocks went a bit crazy along with the VIX that jumped from 17.50 to 38. It&amp;rsquo;s not exactly clear why, the news mention that the Fed might raise its interest rates, the bonds yield have been recently increasing substantially, and the market self-correcting after stocks grew steadily for months in a low VIX environment.
I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly follow the SPX/SPW options daily. But I had taken a snapshot two weeks ago when the market was quiet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Sine Transform via the FFT</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/discrete_sine_transform_fft/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 13:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/discrete_sine_transform_fft/</guid>
      <description>Several months ago, I had a quick look at a recent paper describing how to use Wavelets to price options under stochastic volatility models with a known characteristic function. The more classic method is to use some numerical quadrature directly on the Fourier integral as described in this paper for example. When I read the paper, I was skeptical about the Wavelet approach, since it looked complicated, and with many additional parameters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Finance Books Citing My Papers</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quantitative_finance_books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 13:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quantitative_finance_books/</guid>
      <description>I would have never really expected that when I started writing papers, but little by little there is a growing list of books citing my papers:
 Applied Quantitative Finance for Equity Derivatives by Jherek Healy: the most recent book on equity derivatives refers to several of my papers. In contrast with many other books, the author goes beyond and provides additional insights on the papers. Interest Rate Derivatives Explained: Volume 2: Term Structure and Volatility Modelling by Jörg Kienitz and Peter Casper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benham disc in web canvas</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/benham_disc_in_web_canvas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/benham_disc_in_web_canvas/</guid>
      <description>Around 15 years ago, I wrote a small Java applet to try and show the Benham disk effect. Even back then applets were already passé and Flash would have been more appropriate. These days, no browser support Java applets anymore, and very few web users have Java installed. Flash also mostly disappeared. The web canvas is today&amp;rsquo;s standard allowing to embbed animations in a web page. This effect shows color perception from a succession of black and white pictures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogs on Quantitative Finance</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quantitative_finance_blogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quantitative_finance_blogs/</guid>
      <description>There are not many blogs on quantitative finance that I read. Blogs are not so popular anymore with the advent of the various social networks (facebook, stackoverflow, google plus, reddit, &amp;hellip;). Here is a small list:
 Clarus FT: often interesting statistics on the swap market, clearing, plus the more technical articles from Gary. Quants R Us: A relatively new blog with a promising starting post analyzing Andreasen-Huge one-step local-volatility algorithm with a Spline Fooling around with Quantlib: the blog from Peter Caspers, also relevant to non-Quantlib professionals has original insights such as Smile dynamics by densities or the Supernatural Libor Coupons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Typo in Hyman non-negative constraint - 28 years later</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/typo-in-hyman-non-negative-constraint/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/typo-in-hyman-non-negative-constraint/</guid>
      <description>In their paper &amp;ldquo;Nonnegativity-, Monotonicity-, or Convexity-Preserving Cubic and Quintic Hermite Interpolation&amp;rdquo;, Dougherty, Edelman and Hyman present a simple filter on the first derivatives to maintain positivity of a cubic spline interpolant.
Unfortunately, in their main formula for non-negativity, they made a typo: the equation (3.3) is not consistent with the equation (3.1): the \( \Delta x_{i-1/2} \) is interverted with \( \Delta x_{i+1/2} \).
It was not obvious to find out which equation was wrong since there is no proof in the paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implied Volatility from Black-Scholes price</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implied-volatility-from-black-scholes-price/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implied-volatility-from-black-scholes-price/</guid>
      <description>Dan Stefanica and Rados Radoicic propose a quite good initial guess in their very recent paper An Explicit Implied Volatility Formula. Their formula is simple, fast to compute and results in an implied volatility guess with a relative error of less than 10%.
It is more robust than the rational fraction from Minquiang Li: his rational fraction is only valid for a fixed range of strikes and maturities. The new approximation is mathematically proved accurate across all strikes and all maturities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The VIX starts smiling</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/vix-starts-smiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/vix-starts-smiling/</guid>
      <description>The VIX implied volatilities used to look like a logarithmic function of the strikes. I don&amp;rsquo;t look at them often, but today, I noticed that the VIX had the start of a smile shape.
 1m VIX implied volatilities on March 21, 2017 with strictly positive volume.   Very few strikes trades below the VIX future level (12.9). All of this is likely because the VIX is unusually low: not many people are looking to trade it much lower.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When SVI Breaks Down</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/when-svi-breaks-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/when-svi-breaks-down/</guid>
      <description>In order to fit the implied volatility smile of equity options, one of the most popular parameterization is Jim Gatheral&amp;rsquo;s SVI, which I have written about before here.
It turns out that in the current market conditions, SVI does not work well for short maturities. SPX options expiring on March 24, 2017 (one week) offer a good example. I paid attention to include only options with non zero volume, that is options that are actually traded.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brownian Bridge and Discrete Random Variables</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 14:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/</guid>
      <description>The new Heston discretisation scheme I wrote about a few weeks ago makes use a discrete random variable matching the first five moments of the normal distribution instead of the usual normally distributed random variable, computed via the inverse cumulative distribution function. Their discrete random variable is: $$\xi =	\sqrt{1-\frac{\sqrt{6}}{3}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 &amp;lt; 3,,$$ $$	\xi =-\sqrt{1-\frac{\sqrt{6}}{3}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 &amp;gt; 4,,$$ $$\xi =	\sqrt{1+\sqrt{6}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 = 3,,$$ $$\xi =	-\sqrt{1+\sqrt{6}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 = 4,,$$ with \(U_1 \in \{0,1,&amp;hellip;,7\}\)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new scheme for Heston - Part 2</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 07:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/</guid>
      <description>A couple weeks ago, I wrote about a new Heston discretisation scheme which was at least as accurate as Andersen QE scheme and faster, called DVSS2.
It turns out that it does not behave very well on the following Vanilla forward start option example (which is quite benign). The Heston parameters comes from a calibration to the market and are
$$v_0= 0.0718, \kappa= 1.542, \theta= 0.0762, \sigma= 0.582, \rho= -0.352$$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence between floating-strike and fixed-strike Asian options</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/</guid>
      <description>Many papers present formulae to price Asian options in the Black-Scholes world only for the fixed strike Asian case, that is a contract that pays \( \max(A-K,0)\) at maturity \(T\) where \(A = \sum_{i=0}^{n-1} w_i S(t_i) \) is the Asian average.
More generally, this can be seen as the payoff of a Basket option where the underlyings are just the same asset but at different times. And any Basket option formula can actually be used to price fixed-strike Asian options by letting the correlation correspond to the correlation between the asset at the averaging times and the variances correspond to the variance at each averaging time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelier Normal Volatility Asymptotics</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/</guid>
      <description>It is relatively well known that the Black-Scholes volatility can not grow faster than \(\sqrt{\ln(K)}\). The rule is also sometimes simply stated as &amp;ldquo;the implied variance can not grow faster than linear&amp;rdquo; (in log-moneyness). The proof comes from Roger Lee &amp;ldquo;The moment formula for implied volatility at extreme strikes&amp;rdquo; but the rule was suggested earlier, for example in Hodge&amp;rsquo;s paper from 1996 &amp;ldquo;Arbitrage bounds of the implied volatility strike and term structures of European-style options&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new scheme for Heston</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 07:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled recently upon a new Heston discretisation scheme, in the spirit of Alfonsi, not more complex and more accurate.
My first attempt at coding the scheme resulted in a miserable failure even though the described algorithm looked not too difficult. I started wondering if the paper, from a little known Lithuanian mathematical journal, was any good. Still, the math in it is very well written, with a great emphasis on the settings for each proposition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Andreasen-Huge interpolation - Don&#39;t stay flat</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/</guid>
      <description>Jesper Andreasen and Brian Huge propose an arbitrage-free interpolation method based on a single-step forward Dupire PDE solution in their paper Volatility interpolation. To do so, they consider a piecewise constant representation of the local volatility in maturity time and strike where the number of constants matches the number of market option prices.
An interesting example that shows some limits to the technique as described in Jesper Andreasen and Brian Huge paper comes from Nabil Kahale paper on an arbitrage-free interpolation of volatilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put-Call parity and the log-transformed Black-Scholes PDE</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/put_call_parity_with_log_transformed_pde/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/put_call_parity_with_log_transformed_pde/</guid>
      <description>We will assume zero interest rates and no dividends on the asset \(S\) for clarity. The results can be easily generalized to the case with non-zero interest rates and dividends. Under those assumptions, the Black-Scholes PDE is: $$	\frac{\partial V}{\partial t} + \frac{1}{2}\sigma^2 S^2 \frac{\partial^2 V}{\partial S^2} = 0.$$
An implicit Euler discretisation on a uniform grid in \(S\) of width \(h\) with linear boundary conditions (zero Gamma) leads to:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benaim et al. extrapolation does not work on equities</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/issues_with_bdk_extrapolation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/issues_with_bdk_extrapolation/</guid>
      <description>We have seen earlier that a simple parabola allows to capture the smile of AAPL 1m options surprisingly well. For very high and very low strikes, the parabola does not obey Lee&amp;rsquo;s moments formula (the behavior in the wings needs to be at most linear in variance/log-moneyness).
Extrapolating the volatility smile in the low or high strikes in a smooth \(C^2\) fashion is however not easy. A surprisingly popular so called &amp;ldquo;arbitrage-free&amp;rdquo; method is the extrapolation of Benaim, Dodgson and Kainth developed to remedy the negative density of SABR in interest rates as well as to give more control over the wings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AES for Monte-Carlo</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/aes_for_monte_carlo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/aes_for_monte_carlo/</guid>
      <description>In finance, and also in science, the Mersenne-Twister is the de-factor pseudo-random number generator (PRNG) for Monte-Carlo simulations. By the way, there is a recent 64-bit maximally equidistributed version called MEMT19937 with 53-bit double precision floating point numbers in mind.
D.E. Shaw paper Parallel Random Numbers: As easy as 1, 2, 3 makes a bold remark: since specific AES instructions have been available since 2010 in most x86 processors, why not use them?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Number of regressors in a BSDE</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/number_of_regressors_in_bdse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/number_of_regressors_in_bdse/</guid>
      <description>Last year, I was kindly invited at the workshop on Models and Numerics in Financial Mathematics at the Lorentz center. It was surprinsgly interesting on many different levels. Beside the relatively large gap between academia and the industry, which this workshop was trying to address, one thing that struck me is how difficult it was for people of slightly different specialties to communicate.
It seemed that mathematicians of different countries working on different subjects related to backward stochastic differential equations (BSDEs) would not truly understand each other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting arbitrage - part II</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage2/</guid>
      <description>In my [previous post]((/post/shooting_arbitrage/), I looked at de-arbitraging volatilities of options of a specific maturity with the shooting method. In reality it is not so practical. While the local volatility will be continuous at the given expiry \(T\), it won&amp;rsquo;t be so at the times \( t \lt T \) because of the interpolation or extrapolation in time. If we consider a single market expiry at time \(T\), it is standard practice to extrapolate the implied volatility flatly for \(t \lt T\), that is, \(w(y,t) = v_T(y) t\) where the variance at time \(T\) is defined as \(v_T(y)= \frac{1}{T}w(y,T)\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting arbitrage - part I</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage/</guid>
      <description>In my [previous post]((/post/damghani_dearbitraging_a_weak_smile_on_svi/), I looked at de-arbitraging volatilities of options of a specific maturity with SVI (re-)calibration. The penalty method can be used beyond SVI. For example I interpolate here with a cubic spline on 11 equidistant nodes the original volatility slice that contains arbitrages and then minimize with Levenberg-Marquardt and the negative local variance denominator penalty on 51 equidistant points. This results in a quite small adjustment to the original volatilities:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dearbitraging a weak smile on SVI with Damghani&#39;s method</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/damghani_dearbitraging_a_weak_smile_on_svi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/damghani_dearbitraging_a_weak_smile_on_svi/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I wrote about some calendar spread arbitrages with SVI. Today I am looking at the famous example of butterfly spread arbitrage from Axel Vogt. $$(a, b, m, \rho, \sigma) = (−0.0410, 0.1331, 0.3586, 0.3060, 0.4153)$$ The parameters obey the weak no-arbitrage constraint of Gatheral, and yet produce a negative density, or equivalently, a negative denominator in the local variance Dupire formula. Those parameters are mentioned in Jim Gatheral and Antoine Jacquier paper on arbitrage free SVI volatility surfaces and also in Damghani&amp;rsquo;s paper dearbitraging a weak smile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrage in Zeliade&#39;s SVI example</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi_zeliade_arbitrage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi_zeliade_arbitrage/</guid>
      <description>Zeliade wrote an excellent paper about the calibration of the SVI parameterization for the volatility surface in 2008. I just noticed recently that their example calibration actually contained strong calendar spread arbitrages. This is not too surprising if you look at the parameters, they vary wildly between the first and the second expiry.
   T a b rho m s     0.082 0.027 0.234 0.068 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dupire Local Volatility with Cash Dividends Part 2</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend_part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 17:01:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend_part2/</guid>
      <description>I had a look at how to price under Local Volatility with Cash dividends in my previous post. I still had a somewhat large error in my FDM price. After too much time, I managed to find the culprit, it was the extrapolation of the prices when applying the jump continuity condition \(V(S,t_\alpha^-) = V(S-\alpha, t_\alpha^+) \) for an asset \(S\) with a cash dividend of amount \(\alpha\) at \( t_\alpha \).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dupire Local Volatility with Cash Dividends</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2016 17:01:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend/</guid>
      <description>The Dupire equation for local volatility has been derived under the assumption of Martingality, that means no dividends or interest rates. The extension to continuous dividend yield is described in many papers or books:
With cash dividends however, the Black-Scholes formula is not valid anymore if we suppose that the asset jumps at the dividend date of the dividend amount. There are various relatively accurate approximations available to price an option supposing a constant (spot) volatility and jumps, for example, this one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SVI, SABR, or parabola on AAPL?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi_sabr_or_parabola/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 19:32:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi_sabr_or_parabola/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, I took a look at least squares spline and parabola fits on AAPL 1m options market volatilities. I would have imagined SVI to fit even better since it has 5 parameters, and SABR to do reasonably well.
It turns out that the simple parabola has the lowest RMSE, and SVI is not really better than SABR on that example.
 SVI, SABR, least squares parabola fitted to AAPL 1m options   Note that this is just one single example, unlikely to be representative of anything, but I thought this was interesting that in practice, a simple parabola can compare favorably to more complex models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Filon quadrature for stochastic volatility models</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/filon_for_heston/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 19:08:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/filon_for_heston/</guid>
      <description>A while ago, I have applied a relatively simple adaptive Filon quadrature to the problem of volatility swap pricing. The Filon quadrature is an old quadrature from 1928 that allows to integrate oscillatory integrand like \(f(x)\cos(k x) \) or \(f(x)\sin(k x) \). It turns out that combined with an adaptive Simpson like method, it has many advantages over more generic adaptive quadrature methods like Gauss-Lobatto, which is often used on similar problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Least Squares Rational Function</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/rational_fit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 16:37:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/rational_fit/</guid>
      <description>In my paper &amp;ldquo;Fast and Accurate Analytic Basis Point Volatility&amp;rdquo;, I use a table of Chebyshev polynomials to provide an accurate representation of some function. This is an idea I first saw in the Faddeeva package to represent the cumulative normal distribution with high accuracy, and high performance. It is also simple to find out the Chebyshev polynomials, and which intervals are the most appropriate for those, which makes this technique quite appealing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Least Squares Spline for Volatility Interpolation</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/least_squares_spline/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 18:29:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/least_squares_spline/</guid>
      <description>I am experimenting a bit with least squares splines. Existing algorithms (for example from the NSWC Fortran library) usually work with B-splines, a relatively simple explanation of how it works is given in this paper (I think this is how De Boor coded it in the NSWC library). Interestingly there is an equivalent formulation in terms of standard cubic splines, although it seems that the pseudo code on that paper has errors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mystic Parabola</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/mystic_parabola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 22:13:53 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/mystic_parabola/</guid>
      <description>I recently had some fun trying to work directly with the option chain from the Nasdaq website. The data there is quite noisy, but a simple parabola can still give an amazing fit. I will consider the options of maturity two years as illustration. I also relied on a simple implied volatility algorithm that can be summarized in the following steps:
 Compute a rough guess for the forward price by using interest, borrow curves and by extrapolating the dividends.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
