<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misc on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/categories/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in misc on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 07:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/categories/misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Are traditional banks ready for the 21st century?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/are-tradional-banks-ready-for-the-21st/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/are-tradional-banks-ready-for-the-21st/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow up on my parents phishing scam.
After several weeks, my parents and I were finally able to have a real world meeting with the advisor at the bank. The advisor is a young woman with an obvious background in sales.
In order to process the paperwork around the reimbursement of the phishing scam, the main issue was the request of the original phishing e-mail by the bank, as my mother had deleted the e-mail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yesterday, Pirates Took Over My Parents Bank Account</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/yesterday-pirates-took-over-my-parents-bank-account/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/yesterday-pirates-took-over-my-parents-bank-account/</guid>
      <description>This is the story of their hack.
Yesterday evening, I received a call from my mother, frantic over the phone. She says she sees alerts of withdrawals from her bank account on her phone, with new alerts every 5 minutes or so. I try to ask her if she clicked recently on some e-mail related to her bank. She is so panicked that I don&amp;rsquo;t manage to have an answer. While trying to understand if those alerts are real or not, my wife suggests immediately that my mother should call her bank.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
