<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chase the Devil on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chase the Devil on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 20:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Implying the Probability Density from Market Option Prices (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow-up to my posts on the implied risk-neutral density (RND) of the SPW options before and after the big volatility change that happened in early February with two different techniques: a smoothing spline on the implied volatilities and a Gaussian kernel approach.
The Gaussian kernel (as well as to some extent the smoothing spline) let us believe that there are multiple modes in the distribution (multiple peaks in the density). <a href="/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Senior Developers Don&#39;t Know OO Anymore</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/senior-developers-dont-know-oo-anymore/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/senior-developers-dont-know-oo-anymore/</guid>
      <description>It has been a while since the good old object-oriented (OO) programming is not trendy anymore. Functional programming or more dynamic programming (Python-based) have been the trend, with an excursion in template based programming for C++ guys. Those are not strict categories: Python can be used in a very OO way, but it&amp;rsquo;s not how it is marketed or considered by the community.
Recently, I have seen some of the ugliest refactoring in my life as a programmer, done by someone with at least 10 years of experience programming in Java. <a href="/post/senior-developers-dont-know-oo-anymore/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implying the Probability Density from Market Option Prices</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I showed a plot of the probability implied from SPW options before and after the big volatility change of last week. I created it from a least squares spline fit of the market mid implied volatilities (weighted by the inverse of the bid-ask spread). While it looks reasonable, the underlying technique is not very robust. It is particularly sensitive to the number of options strikes used as spline nodes. <a href="/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where is the S&amp;P 500 going to end?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spx500_bets_after_rates_hike/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 19:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spx500_bets_after_rates_hike/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday the American stocks went a bit crazy along with the VIX that jumped from 17.50 to 38. It&amp;rsquo;s not exactly clear why, the news mention that the Fed might raise its interest rates, the bonds yield have been recently increasing substantially, and the market self-correcting after stocks grew steadily for months in a low VIX environment.
I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly follow the SPX/SPW options daily. But I had taken a snapshot two weeks ago when the market was quiet. <a href="/post/spx500_bets_after_rates_hike/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Sine Transform via the FFT</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/discrete_sine_transform_fft/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 13:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/discrete_sine_transform_fft/</guid>
      <description>Several months ago, I had a quick look at a recent paper describing how to use Wavelets to price options under stochastic volatility models with a known characteristic function. The more classic method is to use some numerical quadrature directly on the Fourier integral as described in this paper for example. When I read the paper, I was skeptical about the Wavelet approach, since it looked complicated, and with many additional parameters. <a href="/post/discrete_sine_transform_fft/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Finance Books Citing My Papers</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quantitative_finance_books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 13:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quantitative_finance_books/</guid>
      <description>I would have never really expected that when I started writing papers, but little by little there is a growing list of books citing my papers:
 Applied Quantitative Finance for Equity Derivatives by Jherek Healy: the most recent book on equity derivatives refers to several of my papers. In contrast with many other books, the author goes beyond and provides additional insights on the papers. Interest Rate Derivatives Explained: Volume 2: Term Structure and Volatility Modelling by Jörg Kienitz and Peter Casper. <a href="/post/quantitative_finance_books/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google phones are overrated</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/google_phones_are_overrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/google_phones_are_overrated/</guid>
      <description>It is a relatively common belief that the vanilla Android experience is better, as it runs smoother. The Samsung Touchwiz is often blamed for making things slow and not more practical.
I have had a Nexus 6 for a couple of years and I noticed the slowdowns after each update, up to a point where it sometimes took a few seconds to open the phone app, or to display the keyboard. <a href="/post/google_phones_are_overrated/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SVN is dead</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svn_is_dead/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svn_is_dead/</guid>
      <description>A few years ago, when Git was rising fast and SVN was already not hype anymore, a friend thought that SVN was for many organizations better suited than Git, with the following classical arguments, which were sound at the time:
 Who needs decentralization for a small team or a small company working together? ‎SVN is proven, works well and is simple to use and put in place.  Each argument is in reality not so strong. <a href="/post/svn_is_dead/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Neural Network in Your CPU</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/the_neural_network_in_your_cpu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/the_neural_network_in_your_cpu/</guid>
      <description>Machine learning and artificial intelligence are the current hype (again). In their new Ryzen processors, AMD advertises the Neural Net Prediction. It turns out this is was already used in their older (2012) Piledriver architecture used for example in the AMD A10-4600M. It is also present in recent Samsung processors such as the one powering the Galaxy S7. What is it really?
The basic idea can be traced to a paper from Daniel Jimenez and Calvin Lin &amp;ldquo;Dynamic Branch Prediction with Perceptrons&amp;rdquo;, more precisely described in the subsequent paper &amp;ldquo;Neural methods for dynamic branch prediction&amp;rdquo;. <a href="/post/the_neural_network_in_your_cpu/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benham disc in web canvas</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/benham_disc_in_web_canvas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/benham_disc_in_web_canvas/</guid>
      <description>Around 15 years ago, I wrote a small Java applet to try and show the Benham disk effect. Even back then applets were already passé and Flash would have been more appropriate. These days, no browser support Java applets anymore, and very few web users have Java installed. Flash also mostly disappeared. The web canvas is today&amp;rsquo;s standard allowing to embbed animations in a web page.
This effect shows color perception from a succession of black and white pictures. <a href="/post/benham_disc_in_web_canvas/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
