<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chase the Devil on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chase the Devil on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 20:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>March 9, 2020 crash - where will CAC40 go?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/mar9-cac40-crash/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/mar9-cac40-crash/</guid>
      <description>The stock market crashed by more than 7% on March 9, 2020. It is one of the most important drop since September 2001. I looked at BNP warrant prices on the CAC40 French index, with a maturity of March 20, 2020 , to see what they would tell about the market direction on the day of the crash. This is really a not-so-scientific experiment.
The quotes I got were quite noisy. <a href="/post/mar9-cac40-crash/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>42</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/42/</guid>
      <description>Today my 6-years old son came with a math homework. The stated goal was to learn the different ways to make 10 out of smaller numbers. I was impressed. Immediately, I wondered
 how many ways are there to make 10 out of smaller numbers?
 This is one of the beauties of maths: a very simple problem, which a 6-years old can understand, may actually be quite fundamental. If you want to solve this in the general case, for any number instead of 10, you end up with the partition function. <a href="/post/42/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numba, Pypy Overrated?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/python-numba-overrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/python-numba-overrated/</guid>
      <description>Many benchmarks show impressive performance gains with the use of Numba or Pypy. Numba allows to compile just-in-time some specific methods, while Pypy takes the approach of compiling/optimizing the full python program: you use it just like the standard python runtime. From those benchmarks, I imagined that those tools would improve my 2D Heston PDE solver performance easily. The initialization part of my program contains embedded for loops over several 10Ks elements. <a href="/post/python-numba-overrated/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 10:05:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I just moved my blog to a static website, created with Hugo, I explain the reasons why here. You can find more about me on my linkedin profile. In addition you might find the following interesting:
 List of quantitative finance papers I have freely available on SSRN TR-BDF2 for Stable American Option Pricing. This is the first draft, not the final version that was published in the Journal of Computational Finance. <a href="/about/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing NaNs in Quadprog</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quadprog-nans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/quadprog-nans/</guid>
      <description>Out of curiosity, I tried quadprog as open-source quadratic programming convex optimizer, as it is looks fast, and the code stays relatively simple. I however stumbled on cases where the algorithm would return NaNs even though my inputs seemed straighforward. Other libraries such as CVXOPT did not have any issues with those inputs.
Searching on the web, I found that I was not the only one to stumble on this kind of issue with quadprog. <a href="/post/quadprog-nans/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Probability of a Netflix Stock Crash</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/nflx-stock-crash-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/nflx-stock-crash-probability/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow up to my previous post where I explore the probability of a TSLA stock crash, reproducing the results of Timothy Klassen.
According to the implied cumulative probability density, TSLA has around 15% chance of crashing below $100. Is this really high compared to other stocks? or is it the interpretation of the data erroneous?
Here I take a look at NFLX (Netflix). Below is the implied volatility according to three different models. <a href="/post/nflx-stock-crash-probability/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Probability of a TSLA Stock Crash</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/tsla-stock-crash-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/tsla-stock-crash-probability/</guid>
      <description>Timothy Klassen had an interesting post on linkedin recently, with the title &amp;ldquo;the options market thinks there is a 16% chance that Tesla will not exist in January 2020&amp;rdquo;. As I was also recently looking at the TSLA options, I was a bit intrigued. I looked at the option chain on July 10th, and implied the European volatility from the American option prices. I then fit a few of my favorite models: Andreasen-Huge with Tikhonov regularization, the lognormal mixture, and a polynomial collocation of degree 7. <a href="/post/tsla-stock-crash-probability/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fourth Moment of the Normal SABR Model</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal-sabr-fourth-moment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal-sabr-fourth-moment/</guid>
      <description>I was wondering if I could use the SABR moments to calibrate a model to SABR parameters directly. It turns out that the SABR moments have relatively simple expressions when \(\beta=0\), that is, for the normal SABR model (with no absorption). This is for the pure SABR stochatic volatility model, not the Hagan approximation. For the Hagan approximation, we would need to use the replication by vanilla options to compute the moments. <a href="/post/normal-sabr-fourth-moment/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implying the Probability Density from Market Option Prices (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow-up to my posts on the implied risk-neutral density (RND) of the SPW options before and after the big volatility change that happened in early February with two different techniques: a smoothing spline on the implied volatilities and a Gaussian kernel approach.
The Gaussian kernel (as well as to some extent the smoothing spline) let us believe that there are multiple modes in the distribution (multiple peaks in the density). <a href="/post/implying-the-probability-density-from-market-option-prices-ii/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Senior Developers Don&#39;t Know OO Anymore</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/senior-developers-dont-know-oo-anymore/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/senior-developers-dont-know-oo-anymore/</guid>
      <description>It has been a while since the good old object-oriented (OO) programming is not trendy anymore. Functional programming or more dynamic programming (Python-based) have been the trend, with an excursion in template based programming for C++ guys. Those are not strict categories: Python can be used in a very OO way, but it&amp;rsquo;s not how it is marketed or considered by the community.
Recently, I have seen some of the ugliest refactoring in my life as a programmer, done by someone with at least 10 years of experience programming in Java. <a href="/post/senior-developers-dont-know-oo-anymore/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
