<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 07:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://chasethedevil.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>When SVI Breaks Down</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/when-svi-breaks-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/when-svi-breaks-down/</guid>
      <description>In order to fit the implied volatility smile of equity options, one of the most popular parameterization is Jim Gatheral&amp;rsquo;s SVI, which I have written about before here. It turns out that in the current market conditions, SVI does not work well for short maturities. SPX options expiring on March 24, 2017 (one week) offer a good example. I paid attention to include only options with non zero volume, that is options that are actually traded. <a href="/post/when-svi-breaks-down/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brownian Bridge and Discrete Random Variables</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 14:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/</guid>
      <description>The new Heston discretisation scheme I wrote about a few weeks ago makes use a discrete random variable matching the first five moments of the normal distribution instead of the usual normally distributed random variable, computed via the inverse cumulative distribution function. Their discrete random variable is: $$\xi = \sqrt{1-\frac{\sqrt{6}}{3}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 &amp;lt; 3\,,$$ $$ \xi =-\sqrt{1-\frac{\sqrt{6}}{3}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 &amp;gt; 4\,,$$ $$\xi = \sqrt{1+\sqrt{6}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 = 3\,,$$ $$\xi = -\sqrt{1+\sqrt{6}} \quad \text{ if } U_1 = 4\,,$$ with \(U_1 \in \{0,1,&amp;hellip;,7\}\) The advantage of the discrete variable is that it is much faster to generate. <a href="/post/brownian-bridge-and-discrete-sampling/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samsung Wireless Printer under Fedora 25</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/samsung_wireless_printer_fedora25/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/samsung_wireless_printer_fedora25/</guid>
      <description>This is a note for those who want to setup a Samsung wireless printer under Linux. It is quite simple, this forum post helped me, the actual useful steps on Fedora 25 are: download tar.gz linux driver from Samsung website. As root, unpack &amp;amp; install: tar xvzf SamsungPrinterInstaller.tar.gz cd uld ./install.sh in the printer menu, lookup for the wireless key (8 digits), connect to the printer Wifi network with a computer using the wireless key, enter the network gateway IP, this is typically http://192.168.3.1, click on Login with user &amp;ldquo;admin&amp;rdquo; and password &amp;ldquo;sec00000&amp;rdquo;, open the network wifi settings and select &amp;ldquo;Easy Wi-Fi Settings&amp;rdquo;, connect back to your wireless network, add the network printer via the printer settings wizard, or alternatively through CUPS interface http://localhost:631. <a href="/post/samsung_wireless_printer_fedora25/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new scheme for Heston - Part 2</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 07:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/</guid>
      <description>A couple weeks ago, I wrote about a new Heston discretisation scheme which was at least as accurate as Andersen QE scheme and faster, called DVSS2. It turns out that it does not behave very well on the following Vanilla forward start option example (which is quite benign). The Heston parameters comes from a calibration to the market and are $$v_0= 0.0718, \kappa= 1.542, \theta= 0.0762, \sigma= 0.582, \rho= -0.352$$ with a maturity of one year. <a href="/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston_part2/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power management and XFCE under Fedora 25</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/xfce_fedora25/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/xfce_fedora25/</guid>
      <description>The gnome shell has been crashing on me more regularly lately. XFCE is a good and fast more tradional desktop, but, from past experiences, it does not play well with power management if you only install it via dnf install @xfce-desktop-environment My typical experience is a black screen after resuming from suspend (sometimes, not always), or hibernate (always) and most of the time I end up just rebooting. It turns out this is all caused by the interaction between the gdm login daemon and xfce. <a href="/post/xfce_fedora25/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence between floating-strike and fixed-strike Asian options</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/</guid>
      <description>Many papers present formulae to price Asian options in the Black-Scholes world only for the fixed strike Asian case, that is a contract that pays \( \max(A-K,0)\) at maturity \(T\) where \(A = \sum_{i=0}^{n-1} w_i S(t_i) \) is the Asian average. More generally, this can be seen as the payoff of a Basket option where the underlyings are just the same asset but at different times. And any Basket option formula can actually be used to price fixed-strike Asian options by letting the correlation correspond to the correlation between the asset at the averaging times and the variances correspond to the variance at each averaging time. <a href="/post/floating_strike_fixed_strike_asian_equivalence/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelier Normal Volatility Asymptotics</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/</guid>
      <description>It is relatively well known that the Black-Scholes volatility can not grow faster than \(\sqrt{\ln(K)}\). The rule is also sometimes simply stated as &amp;ldquo;the implied variance can not grow faster than linear&amp;rdquo; (in log-moneyness). The proof comes from Roger Lee &amp;ldquo;The moment formula for implied volatility at extreme strikes&amp;rdquo; but the rule was suggested earlier, for example in Hodge&amp;rsquo;s paper from 1996 &amp;ldquo;Arbitrage bounds of the implied volatility strike and term structures of European-style options&amp;rdquo;. <a href="/post/normal_volatility_asymptotics/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new scheme for Heston</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 07:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled recently upon a new Heston discretisation scheme, in the spirit of Alfonsi, not more complex and more accurate. My first attempt at coding the scheme resulted in a miserable failure even though the described algorithm looked not too difficult. I started wondering if the paper, from a little known Lithuanian mathematical journal, was any good. Still, the math in it is very well written, with a great emphasis on the settings for each proposition. <a href="/post/a-new-scheme-for-heston/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Andreasen-Huge interpolation - Don&#39;t stay flat</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/</guid>
      <description>Jesper Andreasen and Brian Huge propose an arbitrage-free interpolation method based on a single-step forward Dupire PDE solution in their paper Volatility interpolation. To do so, they consider a piecewise constant representation of the local volatility in maturity time and strike where the number of constants matches the number of market option prices. An interesting example that shows some limits to the technique as described in Jesper Andreasen and Brian Huge paper comes from Nabil Kahale paper on an arbitrage-free interpolation of volatilities. <a href="/post/dont-stay-flat-with-andreasen-huge-interpolation/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put-Call parity and the log-transformed Black-Scholes PDE</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/put_call_parity_with_log_transformed_pde/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/put_call_parity_with_log_transformed_pde/</guid>
      <description>We will assume zero interest rates and no dividends on the asset \(S\) for clarity. The results can be easily generalized to the case with non-zero interest rates and dividends. Under those assumptions, the Black-Scholes PDE is: $$ \frac{\partial V}{\partial t} + \frac{1}{2}\sigma^2 S^2 \frac{\partial^2 V}{\partial S^2} = 0.$$ An implicit Euler discretisation on a uniform grid in \(S\) of width \(h\) with linear boundary conditions (zero Gamma) leads to: $$ V^{k+1}_i - V^{k}_i = \frac{1}{2}\sigma^2 \Delta t S_i^2 \frac{V^{k}_{i+1}-2V^k_{i}+V^{k}_{i-1}}{h^2}.$$ for \(i=1,&amp;hellip;,m-1\) with boundaries $$ V^{k+1}_i - V^{k}_i = 0.$$ for \(i=0,m\). <a href="/post/put_call_parity_with_log_transformed_pde/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
