<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 18:53:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/linux/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Desktops in 2015</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-desktops-in-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 18:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-desktops-in-2015/</guid>
      <description>I seem to never be entirely happy with any of the linux desktops these days. I have used XFCE on Ubuntu quite a bit in the past year, it mostly works, but I still had minor annoyances:
- sometimes (rarely) my laptop would not wake up from sleep.
- notifications sometimes keep popping up too much.
- on my desktop, experienced strong tearing issues with the Radeon graphic card, except with some very specific combination of video player settings and desktop settings (and then I had annoying redraw issue when pushing volume up/down in movies). <a href="/post/linux-desktops-in-2015/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GTK 3.0 / Gnome 3.0 annoyance</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gtk-3.0--gnome-3.0-annoyance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 22:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gtk-3.0--gnome-3.0-annoyance/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s quite incredible that Gnome 3.0 was almost an identical mess as KDE 4.0 had been a year or two earlier. Both are much better now, more stable, but both also still have their issues, and don&amp;rsquo;t feel like a real improvement over Gnome 2.0 or KDE 3.5.
Now the main file manager for Gnome 3.0, Nautilus has buttons with nearly identical icons that mean vastly different things, one is a menu, the other is a list view. <a href="/post/gtk-3.0--gnome-3.0-annoyance/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An SSD instead of a laptop</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/an-ssd-instead-of-a-laptop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/an-ssd-instead-of-a-laptop/</guid>
      <description>Last week, my work laptop died after spilling out some water on its keyboard inadvertently. Fortunately, its SSD was intact.
As the laptop SSD connector (SATA) and power follow the desktop computers standards, and as I use Linux, I just plugged the SSD to my home desktop and booted off the SSD. I had to change slightly the X configuration but otherwise everything worked. Linux is great for that.
The same way, I just plugged the SSD to the desktop at work and it worked. <a href="/post/an-ssd-instead-of-a-laptop/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Hardware Issues</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/random-hardware-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 18:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/random-hardware-issues/</guid>
      <description>Today, after wondering why my desktop computer became so unstable (frequent crashes under Fedora), I found out that the micro usb port of my cell phone has some kind of short circuit. My phone behaves strangely in 2014, it lasted nearly 1 week on battery (I lost it for half of the week), and seems to shutdown for no particular reason once in a while.
On the positive side, I also discovered, after owning my monitor for around 5 years, that it has SD card slots on the side, as well as USB ports. <a href="/post/random-hardware-issues/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrage Free SABR - Another View on Hagan Approach</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/arbitrage-free-sabr---another-view-on-hagan-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/arbitrage-free-sabr---another-view-on-hagan-approach/</guid>
      <description>Several months ago, I took a look attwo interesting recent ways to price under SABR with no arbitrage:
One way is due to Andreasen and Huge, where they find an equivalent local volatility expansion, and then use a one-step finite difference technique to price.The other way is due to Hagan himself, where he numerically solves an approximate PDE in the probability density, and then price with options by integrating on this density. <a href="/post/arbitrage-free-sabr---another-view-on-hagan-approach/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Better Fonts in Fedora than in Ubuntu</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/better-fonts-in-fedora-than-in-ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 13:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/better-fonts-in-fedora-than-in-ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>By default, text in Fedora 19 looks ok but not great. There are good tips to improve fonts on http://fedorasolved.org/Members/khaytsus/improve-fontsAs root user here is what need to be done:&amp;nbsp;cd /etc/fonts/conf.dln -s /usr/share/fontconfig/conf.avail/10-autohint.confln -s /usr/share/fontconfig/conf.avail/11-lcdfilter-default.confyum install freetype-freeworld&amp;nbsp;Reboot, then, in gnome-tweak-tool choose hinting = slight, and antialiasing = rgba. I also choose the liberation sans and liberation mono fonts.I am not sure which one did the trick, but it looks much better (even better than my laptop under Ubuntu, not sure why). <a href="/post/better-fonts-in-fedora-than-in-ubuntu/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving Fedora Another Chance</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/giving-fedora-another-chance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 22:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/giving-fedora-another-chance/</guid>
      <description>I have had some stability issues with the Ubuntu 13.04 on my home computer, not on my laptop. It might be related to hard disk encryption (out of curiosity I encrypted my main hard drive in the installer option, resulting in a usable but quite slow system - it&amp;rsquo;s incredible how much the hard drive is still important for performance). I did not have any particular issue on my work laptop with it. <a href="/post/giving-fedora-another-chance/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unity vs KDE in Virtualbox</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/unity-vs-kde-in-virtualbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/unity-vs-kde-in-virtualbox/</guid>
      <description>The other day I installed the latest Ubuntu 13.04 under a VirtualBox virtual machine using Windows as host. To my surprise, unity failed to launch properly on the virtual machine reboot, with compiz complaining, something I have sometimes seen on my work laptop. It&amp;rsquo;s more surprising in a VM since it is in a way much more standard (no strange graphic card, no strange driver, the same stuff for every VirtualBox user (maybe I&amp;rsquo;m wrong there? <a href="/post/unity-vs-kde-in-virtualbox/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenSuse 12.2</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/opensuse-12.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 10:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/opensuse-12.2/</guid>
      <description>After too many upgrades of Ubuntu, and switching from Gnome to KDE and back, my Ubuntu system became behaving strangely in KDE: authorization issues, frequent crashes, pulseaudio &amp;amp; ardour problems. I decided to give another try to OpenSuse, as Linux makes it easy to switch system without losing too much time reinstalling the useful applications.
It&amp;rsquo;s been only a few days, but I am pleasantly surprised with OpenSuse. It feels more polished than Kubuntu. <a href="/post/opensuse-12.2/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pretty Fonts in Chrome with Linux</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pretty-fonts-in-chrome-with-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2012 18:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pretty-fonts-in-chrome-with-linux/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s a bit incredible, but in 2012, some linux distros (like Fedora, or Kubuntu) still have trouble to have pretty fonts everywhere. I found a nice tip initially for Google Chrome but that seems to improve more than Chrome: create ~/.fonts.conf with the following:
[match target=&amp;ldquo;font&amp;rdquo;]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [edit name=&amp;ldquo;autohint&amp;rdquo; mode=&amp;ldquo;assign&amp;rdquo;]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [bool]true[/bool]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [/edit]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [edit name=&amp;ldquo;hinting&amp;rdquo; mode=&amp;ldquo;assign&amp;rdquo;]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [bool]true[/bool]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [/edit] <a href="/post/pretty-fonts-in-chrome-with-linux/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
