<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>linux on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in linux on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 07:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Desktop Linux in 2022</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-in-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-in-2022/</guid>
      <description>I have been a long time user of Fedora at work and have been happy quite happy about it. Around 6 months ago, I moved to Manjaro under VirtualBox in a Windows host, because the company imposes the use of a VPN client that does not run on Linux. It&amp;rsquo;s much less great for several reasons:
 VirtualBox makes everything graphics much slower. It is still way better than WSL2 as I found WSL2 to be a poor man&amp;rsquo;s Linux, where graphics is via some half broken X11 client for Windows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Github and SSH setup</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/github-and-ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/github-and-ssh/</guid>
      <description>Github recently moved to support only ssh access via public/private keys. As I use github to host this blog, I was impacted.
The setup on Linux is not very complicated, and relatively well documented on Github itself but all the steps are not listed in a simplistic manner, and some Google search is still required to find out how to setup multiple private keys for various different servers or different repos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samsung Wireless Printer under Fedora 25</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/samsung_wireless_printer_fedora25/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/samsung_wireless_printer_fedora25/</guid>
      <description>This is a note for those who want to setup a Samsung wireless printer under Linux. It is quite simple, this forum post helped me, the actual useful steps on Fedora 25 are:
 download tar.gz linux driver from Samsung website. As root, unpack &amp;amp; install:  tar xvzf SamsungPrinterInstaller.tar.gz cd uld ./install.sh  in the printer menu, lookup for the wireless key (8 digits), connect to the printer Wifi network with a computer using the wireless key, enter the network gateway IP, this is typically http://192.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power management and XFCE under Fedora 25</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/xfce_fedora25/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/xfce_fedora25/</guid>
      <description>The gnome shell has been crashing on me more regularly lately. XFCE is a good and fast more tradional desktop, but, from past experiences, it does not play well with power management if you only install it via
dnf install @xfce-desktop-environment My typical experience is a black screen after resuming from suspend (sometimes, not always), or hibernate (always) and most of the time I end up just rebooting. It turns out this is all caused by the interaction between the gdm login daemon and xfce.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Desktops in 2015</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-desktops-in-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 18:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-desktops-in-2015/</guid>
      <description>I seem to never be entirely happy with any of the linux desktops these days. I have used XFCE on Ubuntu quite a bit in the past year, it mostly works, but I still had minor annoyances:
 sometimes (rarely) my laptop would not wake up from sleep. notifications sometimes keep popping up too much. on my desktop, experienced strong tearing issues with the Radeon graphic card, except with some very specific combination of video player settings and desktop settings (and then I had annoying redraw issue when pushing volume up/down in movies).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GTK 3.0 / Gnome 3.0 annoyance</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gtk-3.0--gnome-3.0-annoyance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 22:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gtk-3.0--gnome-3.0-annoyance/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s quite incredible that Gnome 3.0 was almost an identical mess as KDE 4.0 had been a year or two earlier. Both are much better now, more stable, but both also still have their issues, and don&amp;rsquo;t feel like a real improvement over Gnome 2.0 or KDE 3.5.
Now the main file manager for Gnome 3.0, Nautilus has buttons with nearly identical icons that mean vastly different things, one is a menu, the other is a list view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An SSD instead of a laptop</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/an-ssd-instead-of-a-laptop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/an-ssd-instead-of-a-laptop/</guid>
      <description>Last week, my work laptop died after spilling out some water on its keyboard inadvertently. Fortunately, its SSD was intact.
As the laptop SSD connector (SATA) and power follow the desktop computers standards, and as I use Linux, I just plugged the SSD to my home desktop and booted off the SSD. I had to change slightly the X configuration but otherwise everything worked. Linux is great for that
The same way, I just plugged the SSD to the desktop at work and it worked.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Hardware Issues</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/random-hardware-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 18:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/random-hardware-issues/</guid>
      <description>Today, after wondering why my desktop computer became so unstable (frequent crashes under Fedora), I found out that the micro usb port of my cell phone has some kind of short circuit. My phone behaves strangely in 2014, it lasted nearly 1 week on battery (I lost it for half of the week), and seems to shutdown for no particular reason once in a while.
On the positive side, I also discovered, after owning my monitor for around 5 years, that it has SD card slots on the side, as well as USB ports.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrage Free SABR - Another View on Hagan Approach</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/arbitrage-free-sabr---another-view-on-hagan-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/arbitrage-free-sabr---another-view-on-hagan-approach/</guid>
      <description>Several months ago, I took a look attwo interesting recent ways to price under SABR with no arbitrage:
One way is due to Andreasen and Huge, where they find an equivalent local volatility expansion, and then use a one-step finite difference technique to price.The other way is due to Hagan himself, where he numerically solves an approximate PDE in the probability density, and then price with options by integrating on this density.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Better Fonts in Fedora than in Ubuntu</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/better-fonts-in-fedora-than-in-ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 13:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/better-fonts-in-fedora-than-in-ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>By default, text in Fedora 19 looks ok but not great. There are good tips to improve fonts on http://fedorasolved.org/Members/khaytsus/improve-fontsAs root user here is what need to be done:&amp;nbsp;cd /etc/fonts/conf.dln -s /usr/share/fontconfig/conf.avail/10-autohint.confln -s /usr/share/fontconfig/conf.avail/11-lcdfilter-default.confyum install freetype-freeworld&amp;nbsp;Reboot, then, in gnome-tweak-tool choose hinting = slight, and antialiasing = rgba. I also choose the liberation sans and liberation mono fonts.I am not sure which one did the trick, but it looks much better (even better than my laptop under Ubuntu, not sure why).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving Fedora Another Chance</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/giving-fedora-another-chance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 22:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/giving-fedora-another-chance/</guid>
      <description>I have had some stability issues with the Ubuntu 13.04 on my home computer, not on my laptop. It might be related to hard disk encryption (out of curiosity I encrypted my main hard drive in the installer option, resulting in a usable but quite slow system - it&amp;rsquo;s incredible how much the hard drive is still important for performance). I did not have any particular issue on my work laptop with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unity vs KDE in Virtualbox</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/unity-vs-kde-in-virtualbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/unity-vs-kde-in-virtualbox/</guid>
      <description>The other day I installed the latest Ubuntu 13.04 under a VirtualBox virtual machine using Windows as host. To my surprise, unity failed to launch properly on the virtual machine reboot, with compiz complaining, something I have sometimes seen on my work laptop. It&amp;rsquo;s more surprising in a VM since it is in a way much more standard (no strange graphic card, no strange driver, the same stuff for every VirtualBox user (maybe I&amp;rsquo;m wrong there?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenSuse 12.2</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/opensuse-12.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 10:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/opensuse-12.2/</guid>
      <description>After too many upgrades of Ubuntu, and switching from Gnome to KDE and back, my Ubuntu system became behaving strangely in KDE: authorization issues, frequent crashes, pulseaudio and ardour problems. I decided to give another try to OpenSuse, as Linux makes it easy to switch system without losing too much time reinstalling the useful applications.
It&amp;rsquo;s been only a few days, but I am pleasantly surprised with OpenSuse. It feels more polished than Kubuntu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pretty Fonts in Chrome with Linux</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pretty-fonts-in-chrome-with-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2012 18:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pretty-fonts-in-chrome-with-linux/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s a bit incredible, but in 2012, some linux distros (like Fedora, or Kubuntu) still have trouble to have pretty fonts everywhere. I found a nice tip initially for Google Chrome but that seems to improve more than Chrome: create ~/.fonts.conf with the following:
[match target=&#34;font&#34;]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [edit name=&#34;autohint&#34; mode=&#34;assign&#34;]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [bool]true[/bool]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [/edit]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [edit name=&#34;hinting&#34; mode=&#34;assign&#34;]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [bool]true[/bool]
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; [/edit]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fedora 17 vs Ubuntu 12.04</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/fedora-17-vs-ubuntu-12.04/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2012 18:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/fedora-17-vs-ubuntu-12.04/</guid>
      <description>I had the bad idea to upgrade to the beta Ubuntu 12.10. Something awfully broke in the upgrade. After too much struggling with apt-get &amp;amp; dpkg, I decided to install Fedora 17.
Strangely Fedora feels much faster than Ubuntu 12.04 (the boot time especially). Yum seems also faster than apt-get, especially the update part. Also while the Unity dock is not bad (better than gnome shell dock), the Unity dash thing just makes me crazy, the gnome shell activities, while close, are much easier to use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gnome Shell more stable than Unity on Ubuntu 12.04</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gnome-shell-more-stable-than-unity-on-ubuntu-12.04/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2012 12:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gnome-shell-more-stable-than-unity-on-ubuntu-12.04/</guid>
      <description>Regularly, the unity dock made some applications inaccessible: clicking on the app icon did not show or start the app anymore, a very annoying bug. This is quite incredible given that this version of Ubuntu is supposed to be long term support. So I decided to give one more chance to Gnome Shell. Installing it on Ubuntu 12.04 is simple with this guide. To my surprise it is very stable so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KDE 4.8 finally has a dock</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/kde-4.8-finally-has-a-dock/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2012 13:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/kde-4.8-finally-has-a-dock/</guid>
      <description>KDE 4.8 finally has a dock: you just have to add the plasma icon tasks. Also the flexibility around ALT+TAB is welcome. With Krusader as file manager, Thunderbird and Firefox for email and web, it is becoming a real nice desktop, but it took a while since the very bad KDE 4.0 release.
It is easy to install under ubuntu 11.10 through the backports and seems very stable so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gnome 3 not so crap after all</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gnome-3-not-so-crap-after-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2011 18:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gnome-3-not-so-crap-after-all/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, I was complaining how bad Gnome 3 was. Since I have installed a real dock: docky, it is now much more usable. I can easily switch / launch applications without an annoying full screen change.
In addition I found out that it had a good desktop search (tracker). The ALT+F2 also does some sort of completion, too bad it can not use tracker here as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gnome 3, Unity, Crap</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gnome-3-unity-crap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 19:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/gnome-3-unity-crap/</guid>
      <description>After the upgrate to Ubuntu 11.04 I was directly on Unity. Having a dock on the left side is nice, but unfortunately, it has various bugs which makes it sometimes annoying. Also the menu on top like Mac Os X is not a bad idea, but it breaks many apps (for example Picasa). Then there is the scrollbar insanity, it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to click on to scroll, and again breaks in some apps (for example Eclipse).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pulseaudio Nightmares - Pure ALSA to the Rescue</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pulseaudio-nightmares---pure-alsa-to-the-rescue/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2009 18:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pulseaudio-nightmares---pure-alsa-to-the-rescue/</guid>
      <description>In the latest stable Ubuntu (9.04), pulseaudio still does not work reliably on my hardware (intel HDA with digital SPDIF out). I upgraded to 9.10 and had even more problems. Sound always worked on boot, but often broke down after a while. And I could not find easy ways to make it work other than rebooting... Killing/restarting pulseaudio, looking at the processes using snd did not work.
One thing works wonderfully, pure ALSA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Audio State = Miserable</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-audio-state--miserable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2009 12:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/linux-audio-state--miserable/</guid>
      <description>There are lots of programs for playing MP3 under linux, a few dealing decently with big libraries. But when you start looking for a program that does crossfade well and manage big libraries easily - there is nothing.
Rhythmbox does some crossfade, but crashes when you move manually in the song. Audacious does some crossfade but regularly crashes with crossfade plugin.
The real alternative are AIMP2 or Foobar2000 in Wine. It is quite incredible that you can have good solid crossfade in wine and not natively in Linux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why ArchLinux Is Better Than Ubuntu</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/why-archlinux-is-better-than-ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2008 10:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/why-archlinux-is-better-than-ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>It has been now a week since I have installed ArchLinux on my home computer. I daily use Ubuntu 8.10 at work.
Since the Ubuntu upgrade from 8.04 to 8.10 I have had problems with my Xorg settings. I just found out the nvidia-settings utility does not manage to save the configuration anymore. So I have to lookup on google and try to fix it. And that annoys me. That annoys me because the promess of Ubuntu is that everything works out of the box.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KDE 4.1.3 (again) on ArchLinux</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/kde-4.1.3-again-on-archlinux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2008 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/kde-4.1.3-again-on-archlinux/</guid>
      <description>I tried another silly thing with Linux, ArchLinux. The setup is quite rough as you have to edit many config files manually. But if you know a bit your way around it takes only a few hours to have everything running well. The installation manual on the wiki is detailed enough to correct all eventual mistakes humans do.
I decided to try once more KDE 4 on it, as at first it was just a silly experiment: I was really not sure ArchLinux would be workable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Firefox 3</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/firefox-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2008 11:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/firefox-3/</guid>
      <description>I tried Firefox 3 twice before, while it was in alpha and beta. I was not impressed at all, it seemed buggy (normal for alpha) and I found the new location bar behavior unintuitive. It did not seem that much faster either. So I always quickly went back to Firefox 2.
I tried again recently, funnily, because of a bad Kernel update. One day, after a kernel update, my laptop started to run only at a max of 800Mhz, I did not notice it immediately.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fedora Linux &amp; Apple Bluetooth Keyboard</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/fedora-linux--apple-bluetooth-keyboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2008 20:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/fedora-linux--apple-bluetooth-keyboard/</guid>
      <description>It took me a long time to have the Apple Bluetooth Keyboard (slim aluminium model) working well with Fedora 9. Thanks to the Ubuntu documentation, it is quite easy to establish a connection manually through hidd commands. It was unfortunately much more difficult to have it automatically recognized and not disconnected after a few minutes without use.
The following configuration should work with any other distro and probably other bluetooth keyboards as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fedora 9 Already Stable</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/fedora-9-already-stable/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2008 11:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/fedora-9-already-stable/</guid>
      <description>Fedora 9   I &amp;ldquo;upgraded&amp;rdquo; my home computer to Fedora 9. &amp;ldquo;upgraded&amp;rdquo; because I reinstalled the OS instead of using the upgrade procedure. I have had so many issues with &amp;ldquo;partial&amp;rdquo; upgrades in the past (with any distro).
Although it is the preview/RC1 version, Fedora 9 is already as stable as a release IMHO. No issues so far, it feels more polished than Fedora 8. OpenJDK 1.6 is there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ubuntu 7.10 vs Fedora Core 8 - Gutsy vs Werewolf</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/ubuntu-7.10-vs-fedora-core-8---gutsy-vs-werewolf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2007 16:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/ubuntu-7.10-vs-fedora-core-8---gutsy-vs-werewolf/</guid>
      <description>I was pretty happy with Ubuntu 7.10, but when Fedora 8 came out I decided to give it a try. Last time I tried it it was Core 2 or something like that, and it was NOT good.
At first Fedora 8 looks quite good, has a good Live CD install, reminiscent of Ubuntu. The positive side is that it is based on the latest Kernel. It manages my Thinkpad T42 very well (suspend, hibernate work).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
