<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hardware on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/hardware/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hardware on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 20:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/hardware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Intel failure and the future of computing</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/intel-failures-and-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/intel-failures-and-the-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What has been happening to the INTC stock today may be revealing of the future. The stock dropped more than 16%, mainly because they announced that their 7nm process does not work (well) and they may rely on an external foundry for their processors. Initially, in 2015, they thought they would have 8nm process by 2017, and 7nm by 2018. They are more than 3 years late.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Intel used to be a leader in the manufacturing process for microprocessor. While the company has its share of internal problems, it may also be that we are starting to hit the barrier, where it becomes very difficult to improve on the existing. The end of Moore’s law has been announced many times, it was already a subject 20 years ago. Today, it may be real, if there is only a single company capable of manufacturing processor using a 5nm process (TSMC).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Google phones are overrated</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/google_phones_are_overrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/google_phones_are_overrated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a relatively common belief that the vanilla Android experience is better, as it runs smoother. The Samsung Touchwiz is often blamed for making things slow and not more practical.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have had a Nexus 6 for a couple of years and I noticed the slowdowns after each update, up to a point where it sometimes took a few seconds to open the phone app, or to display the keyboard. I freed up storage, removed some apps but this did not make any difference. This is more or less the same experience that people have with the Samsung devices if &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Android/comments/73necm/with_the_note_8_samsung_no_longer_delivers/&#34;&gt;reddit comments&lt;/a&gt; are to be believed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
