<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Google on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/google/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Google on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2005 14:35:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/google/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Google Sidebar Hotkey Activation</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/google-sidebar-hotkey-activation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2005 14:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/google-sidebar-hotkey-activation/</guid>
      <description>I like the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://desktop.google.com/en/&#34;&gt;Google Desktop&lt;/a&gt; with the sidebar. It shares similarities with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.konfabulator.com/&#34;&gt;Konfabulator&lt;/a&gt;, recently bought by yahoo. They both allow easy access to some custom little widgets that I would call &#34;active&#34;. They are active because they are refreshed periodically with new information (processor usage, news, scratch pad, emails, etc). But while Konfabulator choose to emphasize on visual effects, Google prefers a more standard information presentation. This shows as well in their choice of technologies:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;   &lt;li&gt;Google Sidebar plug-ins are just Windows appz that can take advantage of Google Interfaces. That makes them quite powerful in theory, but programming them is less accessible.&lt;br /&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;   &lt;li&gt;Konfabulator plug-ins are Javascript+XML, the Javascript is not just regular client-side javascript, it can use Konfabulator API (containing many effect and rudimentary network access), and COM objects . That makes them very focused on presentation, and the Internet.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; In the long run, Google choice makes sense, the forthcoming &lt;a href=&#34;http://fortes.com/work&#34;&gt;Avalon&lt;/a&gt; will make visual effects very accessible to windows developers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now back to the subject, I missed the &#39;activation on hotkey&#39; feature from Konfabulator for the Google Sidebar. Fortunately, I a have found a powerful little open-source program, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.autohotkey.com/&#34;&gt;Autohotkey&lt;/a&gt;, that allowed me to do that very quickly. Here is the script I use (it&#39;s a hack since it relies on toolbar size (but not position), but I like the default position and it works (only using floating deskbar, i let you figure out for the non floating version)):&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:Courier New, Courier, monospace;&#34;&gt;F12::&lt;br /&gt;MouseGetPos, X, Y&lt;br /&gt;if WinExist(&#34;ahk_class _GD_Sidebar&#34;)&lt;br /&gt;{&lt;br /&gt;    WinActivate&lt;br /&gt;    BlockInput,On&lt;br /&gt;    MouseClick, left, 160, 16&lt;br /&gt;    MouseMove, X,Y&lt;br /&gt;    BlockInput,Off&lt;br /&gt;    return&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;else if WinExist(&#34;ahk_class ATL:0044A4C8&#34;)&lt;br /&gt;{&lt;br /&gt;    WinActivate&lt;br /&gt;    BlockInput,On&lt;br /&gt;    MouseClick, left,  158,  16&lt;br /&gt;    MouseMove, X,Y&lt;br /&gt;    BlockInput,Off&lt;br /&gt;    return&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
