<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 09:55:32 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Benaim et al. extrapolation does not work on equities</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/issues_with_bdk_extrapolation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/issues_with_bdk_extrapolation/</guid>
      <description>We have seen earlier that a simple parabola allows to capture the smile of AAPL 1m options surprisingly well. For very high and very low strikes, the parabola does not obey Lee&amp;rsquo;s moments formula (the behavior in the wings needs to be at most linear in variance/log-moneyness). Extrapolating the volatility smile in the low or high strikes in a smooth \(C^2\) fashion is however not easy. A surprisingly popular so called &amp;ldquo;arbitrage-free&amp;rdquo; method is the extrapolation of Benaim, Dodgson and Kainth developed to remedy the negative density of SABR in interest rates as well as to give more control over the wings. <a href="/post/issues_with_bdk_extrapolation/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AES for Monte-Carlo</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/aes_for_monte_carlo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/aes_for_monte_carlo/</guid>
      <description>In finance, and also in science, the Mersenne-Twister is the de-factor pseudo-random number generator (PRNG) for Monte-Carlo simulations. By the way, there is a recent 64-bit maximally equidistributed version called MEMT19937 with 53-bit double precision floating point numbers in mind. D.E. Shaw paper Parallel Random Numbers: As easy as 1, 2, 3 makes a bold remark: since specific AES instructions have been available since 2010 in most x86 processors, why not use them? <a href="/post/aes_for_monte_carlo/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A review of Thomas Piketty - Le capital au XXI siecle</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/piketty_capital/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/piketty_capital/</guid>
      <description>I found back some old notes I had written about the book &amp;ldquo;Le capital au XXI siecle&amp;rdquo; from Thomas Piketty. It took me a while to finish that book last summer. So many journalists have written around Piketty, that I had to buy the book and read it. It turns out that some of the criticism I have read is not really founded once one reads the book, but here are other real obvious criticisms that I suprisingly did not hear. <a href="/post/piketty_capital/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Number of regressors in a BSDE</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/number_of_regressors_in_bdse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/number_of_regressors_in_bdse/</guid>
      <description>Last year, I was kindly invited at the workshop on Models and Numerics in Financial Mathematics at the Lorentz center. It was surprinsgly interesting on many different levels. Beside the relatively large gap between academia and the industry, which this workshop was trying to address, one thing that struck me is how difficult it was for people of slightly different specialties to communicate. It seemed that mathematicians of different countries working on different subjects related to backward stochastic differential equations (BSDEs) would not truly understand each other. <a href="/post/number_of_regressors_in_bdse/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting arbitrage - part II</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage2/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I looked at de-arbitraging volatilities of options of a specific maturity with the shooting method. In reality it is not so practical. While the local volatility will be continuous at the given expiry \(T\), it won&amp;rsquo;t be so at the times \( t \lt T \) because of the interpolation or extrapolation in time. If we consider a single market expiry at time \(T\), it is standard practice to extrapolate the implied volatility flatly for \(t \lt T\), that is, \(w(y,t) = v_T(y) t\) where the variance at time \(T\) is defined as \(v_T(y)= \frac{1}{T}w(y,T)\). <a href="/post/shooting_arbitrage2/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shooting arbitrage - part I</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/shooting_arbitrage/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I looked at de-arbitraging volatilities of options of a specific maturity with SVI (re-)calibration. The penalty method can be used beyond SVI. For example I interpolate here with a cubic spline on 11 equidistant nodes the original volatility slice that contains arbitrages and then minimize with Levenberg-Marquardt and the negative local variance denominator penalty on 51 equidistant points. This results in a quite small adjustment to the original volatilities: implied variance with Axel Vogt SVI parameters Interestingly the denominator looks almost constant, close to zero (in reality it is not constant, just close to zero, scales can be misleading): local variance denominator g with Axel Vogt SVI parameters The method does not work with too many nodes, for example 25 nodes was too much for the minimizer to do anything, maybe because there is too much interaction between nodes then. <a href="/post/shooting_arbitrage/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dearbitraging a weak smile on SVI with Damghani&#39;s method</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/damghani_dearbitraging_a_weak_smile_on_svi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/damghani_dearbitraging_a_weak_smile_on_svi/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I wrote about some calendar spread arbitrages with SVI. Today I am looking at the famous example of butterfly spread arbitrage from Axel Vogt. $$(a, b, m, \rho, \sigma) = (−0.0410, 0.1331, 0.3586, 0.3060, 0.4153)$$ The parameters obey the weak no-arbitrage constraint of Gatheral, and yet produce a negative density, or equivalently, a negative denominator in the local variance Dupire formula. Those parameters are mentioned in Jim Gatheral and Antoine Jacquier paper on arbitrage free SVI volatility surfaces and also in Damghani&amp;rsquo;s paper dearbitraging a weak smile. <a href="/post/damghani_dearbitraging_a_weak_smile_on_svi/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrage in Zeliade&#39;s SVI example</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi_zeliade_arbitrage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 09:55:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi_zeliade_arbitrage/</guid>
      <description>Zeliade wrote an excellent paper about the calibration of the SVI parameterization for the volatility surface in 2008. I just noticed recently that their example calibration actually contained strong calendar spread arbitrages. This is not too surprising if you look at the parameters, they vary wildly between the first and the second expiry. T a b rho m s 0.082 0.027 0.234 0.068 0.100 0.028 0.16 0.030 0.125 -1.0 0.074 0.050 0.26 0.032 0.094 -1.0 0.093 0.041 The calendar spread arbitrage is very visible in total variance versus log-moneyness graph: in those coordinates if lines crosses, there is an arbitrage. <a href="/post/svi_zeliade_arbitrage/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dupire Local Volatility with Cash Dividends Part 2</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend_part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 17:01:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend_part2/</guid>
      <description>I had a look at how to price under Local Volatility with Cash dividends in my previous post. I still had a somewhat large error in my FDM price. After too much time, I managed to find the culprit, it was the extrapolation of the prices when applying the jump continuity condition \(V(S,t_\alpha^-) = V(S-\alpha, t_\alpha^+) \) for an asset \(S\) with a cash dividend of amount \(\alpha\) at \( t_\alpha \). <a href="/post/dupire_cash_dividend_part2/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dupire Local Volatility with Cash Dividends</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2016 17:01:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/dupire_cash_dividend/</guid>
      <description>The Dupire equation for local volatility has been derived under the assumption of Martingality, that means no dividends or interest rates. The extension to continuous dividend yield is described in many papers or books: $$\sigma^{\star 2}\left(K, T\right) = \frac{\frac{\partial C}{\partial T}+(r_B-q)K \frac{\partial C}{\partial K} + q C(K,T)}{\frac{1}{2}K^2\frac{\partial^2 C}{\partial K^2}}$$ In this case, \(C\) is a regular market Call option price, that can also be obtained from market volatilities via the Black-Scholes formula. <a href="/post/dupire_cash_dividend/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
