<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Macos on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/macos/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Macos on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2007 01:04:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/macos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Windows</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/switching-to-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2007 01:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/switching-to-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it, I have done it, the unthinkable. I have switched from MacOs X to Windows XP. My idea was first to install Ubuntu on the Mac Mini, but if you want to keep the Mac Os X install, the methods I have read on the web required to use bootcamp. At around the same time I was annoyed by problems I had with bluetooth and Skype in MacOs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, with bootcamp installed I decided to give a try to Windows. And it works quite well on the Mac. As I use it mostly as a media box (movies, photos, jukebox, browser and tablature reader) and not really as a developer, I find Windows quite convenient. I have always preferred Picasa to iPhoto. And moving back to Picasa for my photos is a joy. I can&amp;rsquo;t believe the speed difference between the two apps, and it&amp;rsquo;s not a matter of memory, I have 2gb. The crappy ways iPhotos deals with my folders is over. I am also happy to use again foobar2000 instead of bloated (and limited (only MP3s and MP4s)) iTunes. In my quest to look for a convenient setup, I discovered ProjectM visualisation, also available for MacOs X (with iTunes) and Linux. I am quite impressed with the animations. I have the impression that graphics are much faster under Windows than under MacOs, it&amp;rsquo;s probably due to much better optimized drivers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
