<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>math on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/categories/math/</link>
    <description>Recent content in math on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 07:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/categories/math/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bad papers and the roots of high degree polynomials</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/bad-papers-polynomial-roots/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/bad-papers-polynomial-roots/</guid>
      <description>I was wondering what were exactly the eigenvalues of the Mersenne-Twister random number generator transition matrix. An article by K. Savvidy sparked my interest on this. This article mentioned a poor entropy (sum of log of eigenvalues amplitudes which are greater than 1), with eigenvalues falling almost on the unit circle.
The eigenvalues are also the roots of the characteristic polynomial. It turns out, that for jumping ahead in the random number sequence, we use the characteristic polynomial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>42</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 20:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/42/</guid>
      <description>Today my 6-years old son came with a math homework. The stated goal was to learn the different ways to make 10 out of smaller numbers. I was impressed. Immediately, I wondered
 how many ways are there to make 10 out of smaller numbers?
 This is one of the beauties of maths: a very simple problem, which a 6-years old can understand, may actually be quite fundamental. If you want to solve this in the general case, for any number instead of 10, you end up with the partition function.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Sine Transform via the FFT</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/discrete_sine_transform_fft/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 13:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/discrete_sine_transform_fft/</guid>
      <description>Several months ago, I had a quick look at a recent paper describing how to use Wavelets to price options under stochastic volatility models with a known characteristic function. The more classic method is to use some numerical quadrature directly on the Fourier integral as described in this paper for example. When I read the paper, I was skeptical about the Wavelet approach, since it looked complicated, and with many additional parameters.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
