<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>book on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/book/</link>
    <description>Recent content in book on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2008 17:06:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Option, Futures and Other Derivatives Book Review</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/option-futures-and-other-derivatives-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2008 17:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/option-futures-and-other-derivatives-book-review/</guid>
      <description>Option, Futures and Other Derivatives is by far the most popular book in finance. You will find it in every finance company, on many desks.
It is a very good introduction for people not familiar with standard financial products. This kind of book is unavoidable to understand the basis. It goes also beyond with the chapters on pricing and hedging. These 2 chapters make one understand many other book. If one understands the Black and Scholze formula, one can easily approach many other pricing formula, as in a way, there are all similar in their approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structured Equity Derivatives Book Review</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/structured-equity-derivatives-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2008 16:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/structured-equity-derivatives-book-review/</guid>
      <description>If one has to learn about equity derivatives, beside the classic Option, Futures and Other Derivativesfrom Hull, Structured Equity Derivativesby Harry M Kat is a must read.His ideas are presented in a software developer friendly way, as his goal is to show how different equity derivatives products are behind the scenes, very similar.I enjoyed the variety of exotic products presented and the very detailed way in which they are explained.The book is filled up with graphs, which is a good thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Concurrency In Practice Book Review</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/java-concurrency-in-practice-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2007 16:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/java-concurrency-in-practice-book-review/</guid>
      <description>My reference book on Java concurrency is Doug Lea&amp;#39;s Concurrent Programming in Java: Design Principles and Patterns. He is one of the authors of this new book, Java Concurrency In Practice. There is also Joshua Bloch, author of Effective Java, that many people love (but I am less a fan of it, even if I would recommend it to Java newbies), and author of Java Puzzlers, that I found more fun.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Software Books - 2006 version</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books-2006-version/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2006 14:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books-2006-version/</guid>
      <description>Here is an update of the most interesting software books I found interesting. I already made such a list in 2005:
 Object Oriented Software Construction, 2nd Ed, by Bertrand Meyer. This made me understand why OOP is important, what is important in OOP and why it is still relevant. It contains lots of important guidelines you can apply to better design programs. One famous quote is &#34;Real systems have no top&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms in Java (Third Edition) Book Review</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/algorithms-in-java-third-edition-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2006 12:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/algorithms-in-java-third-edition-book-review/</guid>
      <description>The book Algorithms in Javais huge, but unlike the usual huge books, the content is very interesting. It can be used as reference material, or as toilet book (to learn things while you&#39;re wasting time in the toilets).
You will learn simple things, like what is the &#34;raison d&#39;être&#34; of linked lists. The author gives very good examples to illustrate his propositions. He explains through the sieve of erathostene and through Josephus problem the advantages of arrays or linked list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SOA and B. Meyer</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/soa-and-b.-meyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2006 15:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/soa-and-b.-meyer/</guid>
      <description>While rereading parts of Object Oriented Software Construction from B. Meyer, I still find valuable information I overlooked. In the part about functional decomposition where he argues pro and cons of top-down / bottom-up approaches, he has the intuition of the current SOA hype. By showing that
 Real systems have no top.
 He suggests that the only way to build complex software is through a service oriented architecture. Of course SOA is a very old concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non Fiction Books (Mostly Software Programming) Before 2003</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/non-fiction-books-mostly-software-programming-before-2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2006 15:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/non-fiction-books-mostly-software-programming-before-2003/</guid>
      <description>A page with useful reference for me as I don&#39;t own each one of these books. It can provides you a very short review non-commercial biased.
2003
Programming Jakarta Struts (O&#39;Reilly - Chuck Cavaness) much better than Manning book. Explains struts very clearly with a more interesting example. Not enough on how to design your application for use with the evil ActionForm. Almost nothing on Struts 1.1 features. Nothing on common problems encountered while building web applications, or even about on how to design them using struts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Portal Development Book Review</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/professional-portal-development-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2005 12:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/professional-portal-development-book-review/</guid>
      <description>I just finished reading Professional Portal Development With Open Source Tools (Wiley).
The Good:
I enjoyed Chapter 1, it gives a good presentation of Portlets for someone who does not know much about it. It is a chapter one can use as a reference to verify some specific details of how Portlets are working. It is a bit similar to JSR 168 specifications, but I found it more detailed and well written.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Software Books</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2005 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books/</guid>
      <description>A friend asked me for a list, here is it. I found those books the most interesting ones among those I have read about software in the past year or two:
 Artificial Intelligence through Prolog, by Neil C. Rowe (Prentice-Hall): if you don&#39;t remember much about Prolog, it&#39;s a good book. It details how Prolog interpreters work. File Systems Forensic Analysis, by Brian Carrier (Addison Wesley): everything you need to know about disks and file systems, every trick to recover lost data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 Years Later: Still EJBs</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/7-years-later-still-ejbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2005 16:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/7-years-later-still-ejbs/</guid>
      <description>In 1998, a student of my school had a project with Sun about EJBs. This was the beginning of EJBs, they were not public, and there was no J2EE. At that time he found it utterly complicated, and had difficulties to understand why they made it so complicated.
In 2000, I worked for a company who had built in-house most components of a today J2EE application server. For example, they had their own unified messaging system, on the JSP side, they were already using custom tags, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Books Roundup Updated</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spring-books-roundup-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2005 16:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spring-books-roundup-updated/</guid>
      <description>I am completing my Spring Books Roundupbooks with 2 new books:Pro Spring, by Apress: a lengthy book, with some unnecessary information, but good overall. I did not like the Part 1, there is not much content in it. Fortunately, Part 2 is much better, dependency injection is very well described, almost on par, with the Fowler article of reference. Other Spring areas are well covered, in a similar manner as in Wrox book, except Java Server Faces, absent from the book, and nothing on Swing as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Books Roundup</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spring-books-roundup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2005 11:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/spring-books-roundup/</guid>
      <description>Spring is hip these days, so I decided to learn a bit more about it. I had used Avalon a while ago, I was attracted by its design by component and the way it seemed to lay out a proper infrastructure to build a server application. In the end, I was a bit disappointed, it required a bit too much glue code for my taste and did not provide that much in exchange.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Puzzlers - Can you figure this out?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/java-puzzlers-can-you-figure-this-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2005 16:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/java-puzzlers-can-you-figure-this-out/</guid>
      <description>The book Java Puzzlers is quite good. I don&#39;t think anyone can get every puzzle right. This shows again how you can very easily make someone fail interviews if you ask too silly questions. I suppose that if people were asking those questions they would not expect the right answers, but study the candidate reactions.
Here is a sample:
public class DosEquis {
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;public static void main(String[] args) {</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Prolog Better Suited Than SQL?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/is-prolog-better-suited-than-sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2005 15:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/is-prolog-better-suited-than-sql/</guid>
      <description>I am currently reading a Prolog book Artificial Intelligence Through Prolog, I have been doing a bit of Prolog when I was very young and wanted to refresh my memory a bit. It is a very interesting read, especially when I take the viewpoint of our current application where no ACID compliance is required.
It seems to me that all the logic we coded to parametrize SQL queries and construct them dynamically could have been avoided if we had chosen Prolog as Prolog expressions would have been very natural to use in our project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inside the Java Virtual Machine</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/inside-the-java-virtual-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2005 11:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/inside-the-java-virtual-machine/</guid>
      <description>I am reading an old book, Inside the Java Virtual Machine. Some old books don&#39;t age, and this is one of them. The chapter on the Java Virtual Machine is just excellent and should be read by every Java developer. It explains each step a JVM does when you run a Java program, very clearly.
You could get plenty of stupid interview questions from it like: How is the Java stack used?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
