<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/book/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2008 17:06:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/book/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Option, Futures and Other Derivatives Book Review</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/option-futures-and-other-derivatives-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2008 17:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/option-futures-and-other-derivatives-book-review/</guid>
      <description>Option, Futures and Other Derivatives is by far the most popular book in finance. You will find it in every finance company, on many desks.
It is a very good introduction for people not familiar with standard financial products. This kind of book is unavoidable to understand the basis. It goes also beyond with the chapters on pricing and hedging. These 2 chapters make one understand many other book. If one understands the Black and Scholze formula, one can easily approach many other pricing formula, as in a way, there are all similar in their approach. <a href="/post/option-futures-and-other-derivatives-book-review/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structured Equity Derivatives Book Review</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/structured-equity-derivatives-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2008 16:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/structured-equity-derivatives-book-review/</guid>
      <description>If one has to learn about equity derivatives, beside the classic Option, Futures and Other Derivatives from Hull, Structured Equity Derivatives by Harry M Kat is a must read.
His ideas are presented in a software developer friendly way, as his goal is to show how different equity derivatives products are behind the scenes, very similar.
I enjoyed the variety of exotic products presented and the very detailed way in which they are explained. <a href="/post/structured-equity-derivatives-book-review/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Concurrency In Practice Book Review</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/java-concurrency-in-practice-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2007 16:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/java-concurrency-in-practice-book-review/</guid>
      <description>My reference book on Java concurrency is Doug Lea&amp;#39;s Concurrent Programming in Java: Design Principles and Patterns. He is one of the authors of this new book, Java Concurrency In Practice. There is also Joshua Bloch, author of Effective Java, that many people love (but I am less a fan of it, even if I would recommend it to Java newbies), and author of Java Puzzlers, that I found more fun. <a href="/post/java-concurrency-in-practice-book-review/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Software Books - 2006 version</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books---2006-version/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2006 14:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books---2006-version/</guid>
      <description>Here is an update of the most interesting software books I found interesting. I already made such a list in 2005:
 Object Oriented Software Construction, 2nd Ed, by Bertrand Meyer. This made me understand why OOP is important, what is important in OOP and why it is still relevant. It contains lots of important guidelines you can apply to better design programs. One famous quote is &amp;ldquo;Real systems have no top&amp;rdquo;. <a href="/post/good-software-books---2006-version/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms in Java (Third Edition) Book Review</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/algorithms-in-java-third-edition-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2006 12:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/algorithms-in-java-third-edition-book-review/</guid>
      <description>The book Algorithms in Javais huge, but unlike the usual huge books, the content is very interesting. It can be used as reference material, or as toilet book (to learn things while you&amp;rsquo;re wasting time in the toilets).
You will learn simple things, like what is the &amp;ldquo;raison d&amp;rsquo;être&amp;rdquo; of linked lists. The author gives very good examples to illustrate his propositions. He explains through the sieve of erathostene and through Josephus problem the advantages of arrays or linked list. <a href="/post/algorithms-in-java-third-edition-book-review/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SOA and B. Meyer</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/soa-and-b.-meyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2006 15:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/soa-and-b.-meyer/</guid>
      <description>While rereading parts of &amp;quot;Object Oriented Software Construction&amp;quot; from B. Meyer, I still find valuable information I overlooked. In the part about functional decomposition where he argues pro and cons of top-down / bottom-up approaches, he has the intuition of the current SOA hype. By showing that Real systems have no top. 
He suggests that the only way to build complex software is through a service oriented architecture. Of course SOA is a very old concept. <a href="/post/soa-and-b.-meyer/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non Fiction Books (Mostly Software Programming) Before 2003</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/non-fiction-books-mostly-software-programming-before-2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2006 15:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/non-fiction-books-mostly-software-programming-before-2003/</guid>
      <description>A page with useful reference for me as I don&amp;rsquo;t own each one of these books. It can provides you a very short review non-commercial biased.
2003
Programming Jakarta Struts (O&amp;rsquo;Reilly - Chuck Cavaness) much better than Manning book. Explains struts very clearly with a more interesting example. Not enough on how to design your application for use with the evil ActionForm. Almost nothing on Struts 1.1 features. Nothing on common problems encountered while building web applications, or even about on how to design them using struts. <a href="/post/non-fiction-books-mostly-software-programming-before-2003/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Portal Development Book Review</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/professional-portal-development-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2005 12:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/professional-portal-development-book-review/</guid>
      <description>I just finished reading Professional Portal Development With Open Source Tools (Wiley).
The Good:
I enjoyed Chapter 1, it gives a good presentation of Portlets for someone who does not know much about it. It is a chapter one can use as a reference to verify some specific details of how Portlets are working. It is a bit similar to JSR 168 specifications, but I found it more detailed and well written. <a href="/post/professional-portal-development-book-review/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Software Books</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2005 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/good-software-books/</guid>
      <description>A friend asked me for a list, here is it. I found those books the most interesting ones among those I have read about software in the past year or two:
 Artificial Intelligence through Prolog, by Neil C. Rowe (Prentice-Hall): if you don&amp;rsquo;t remember much about Prolog, it&amp;rsquo;s a good book. It details how Prolog interpreters work. File Systems Forensic Analysis, by Brian Carrier (Addison Wesley): everything you need to know about disks and file systems, every trick to recover lost data. <a href="/post/good-software-books/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 Years Later: Still EJBs</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/7-years-later-still-ejbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2005 16:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/7-years-later-still-ejbs/</guid>
      <description>In 1998, a student of my school had a project with Sun about EJBs. This was the beginning of EJBs, they were not public, and there was no J2EE. At that time he found it utterly complicated, and had difficulties to understand why they made it so complicated.
In 2000, I worked for a company who had built in-house most components of a today J2EE application server. For example, they had their own unified messaging system, on the JSP side, they were already using custom tags, etc. <a href="/post/7-years-later-still-ejbs/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
