<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scala on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/scala/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Scala on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 13:58:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/scala/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Flat Volatility Surfaces &amp; Discrete Dividends</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/flat-volatility-surfaces--discrete-dividends/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/flat-volatility-surfaces--discrete-dividends/</guid>
      <description>In papers around volatility and cash (discrete) dividends, we often encounter the example of the flat volatility surface. For example, the OpenGamma paper presents this graph:

It shows that if the Black volatility surface is fully flat, there are jumps in the pure volatility surface (corresponding to a process that includes discrete dividends in a consistent manner) at the dividend dates or equivalently if the pure volatility surface is flat, the Black volatility jumps. <a href="/post/flat-volatility-surfaces--discrete-dividends/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning &amp; Quantitative Finance</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/machine-learning--quantitative-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 12:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/machine-learning--quantitative-finance/</guid>
      <description>There is an interesting course on Machine Learning on Coursera, it does not require much knowledge and yet manages to teach quite a lot.
I was struck by the fact that most techniques and ideas apply also to problems in quantitative finance.
Linear regression: used for example in the Longstaff-Schwartz approach to price Bermudan options with Monte-Carlo. Interestingly the teacher insists on feature normalization, something we can forget easily, especially with the polynomial features. <a href="/post/machine-learning--quantitative-finance/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-Random vs Quasi-Random Numbers</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pseudo-random-vs-quasi-random-numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2014 17:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/pseudo-random-vs-quasi-random-numbers/</guid>
      <description>Quasi-Random numbers (like Sobol) are a relatively popular way in finance to improve the Monte-Carlo convergence compared to more classic Pseudo-Random numbers (like Mersenne-Twister). Behind the scenes one has to be a bit more careful about the dimension of the problem as the Quasi-Random numbers depends on the dimension (defined by how many random variables are independent from each other).
For a long time, Sobol was limited to 40 dimensions using the so called Bratley-Fox direction numbers (his paper actually gives the numbers for 50 dimensions). <a href="/post/pseudo-random-vs-quasi-random-numbers/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating an oscillatory function</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/integrating-an-oscillatory-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 16:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/integrating-an-oscillatory-function/</guid>
      <description>Recently, some instabilities were noticed in the Carr-Lee seasoned volatility swap price in some situations. The Carr-Lee seasoned volatility swap price involve the computation of a double integral. The inner integral is really the problematic one as the integrand can be highly oscillating.

I&amp;nbsp; first found a somewhat stable behavior using a specific adaptive Gauss-Lobatto implementation (the one from Espelid) and a change of variable. But it was not very satisfying to see that the outer integral was stable only with another specific adaptive Gauss-Lobatto (the one from Gander &amp;amp; Gauschi, present in Quantlib). <a href="/post/integrating-an-oscillatory-function/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The elusive reference: the Lamperti transform</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/the-elusive-reference-the-lamperti-transform/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 11:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/the-elusive-reference-the-lamperti-transform/</guid>
      <description>Without knowing that it was a well known general concept, I first noticed the use of the Lamperti transform in the Andersen-Piterbarg &amp;ldquo;Interest rate modeling&amp;rdquo; book p292 &amp;ldquo;finite difference solutions for general phi&amp;rdquo;. &amp;nbsp;Pat Hagan used that transformation for a better discretization&amp;nbsp; of the arbitrage free SABR PDE model.I then started to notice the use of this transformation in many more papers. The first one I saw naming it &amp;ldquo;Lamperti transform&amp;rdquo; was the paper from Ait-Sahalia &amp;ldquo;Maximum likelyhood estimation of discretely sampled diffusions: a closed-form approximation approach&amp;rdquo;. <a href="/post/the-elusive-reference-the-lamperti-transform/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barrier options under negative rates: complex numbers to the rescue</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/barrier-options-under-negative-rates-complex-numbers-to-the-rescue/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2014 11:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/barrier-options-under-negative-rates-complex-numbers-to-the-rescue/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon an unexpected problem: the one touch barrier formula can break down under negative rates. While negative rates can sound fancy, they are actually quite real on some markets. Combined with relatively low volatilities, this makes the standard Black-Scholes one touch barrier formula blow up because somewhere the square root of a negative number is taken.
At first, I had the idea to just floor the number to 0. <a href="/post/barrier-options-under-negative-rates-complex-numbers-to-the-rescue/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial Guesses for SVI - A Summary</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/initial-guesses-for-svi---a-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 10:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/initial-guesses-for-svi---a-summary/</guid>
      <description>I have been looking at various ways of finding initial guesses for SVI calibration (Another SVI Initial Guess, More SVI Initial Guesses, SVI and long maturities issues). I decided to write a paper summarizing this. I find that the process of writing a paper makes me think more carefully about a problem.
In this case, it turns out that the Vogt initial guess method (guess via asymptotes and minimum variance) is actually very good as long as one has a good way to lookup the asymptotes (the data is not always convex, while SVI is) and as long as rho is not close to -1, that is for long maturity affine like smiles, where SVI is actually more difficult to calibrate properly due to the over-parameterisation in those cases. <a href="/post/initial-guesses-for-svi---a-summary/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Behavior of SVI vs SABR</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/asymptotic-behavior-of-svi-vs-sabr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 12:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/asymptotic-behavior-of-svi-vs-sabr/</guid>
      <description>The variance under SVI becomes linear when the log-moneyness is very large in absolute terms. The lognormal SABR formula with beta=0 or beta=1 has a very different behavior. Of course, the theoretical SABR model has actually a different asymptotic behavior.
As an illustration, we calibrate SABR (with two different values of beta) and SVI against the same implied volatility slice and look at the wings behavior. 
While the Lee moments formula implies that the variance should be at most linear, something that the SABR formula does not respect. <a href="/post/asymptotic-behavior-of-svi-vs-sabr/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SVI and long maturities issues</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi-and-long-maturities-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 12:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/svi-and-long-maturities-issues/</guid>
      <description>On long maturities equity options, the smile is usually very much like a skew:&amp;nbsp; very little curvature. This usually means that the SVI rho will be very close to -1, in a similar fashion as what can happen for the the correlation parameter of a real stochastic volatility model (Heston, SABR).
In terms of initial guess, we looked at the more usual use cases and showed that matching a parabola at the minimum variance point often leads to a decent initial guess if one has an ok estimate of the wings. <a href="/post/svi-and-long-maturities-issues/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More SVI Initial Guesses</title>
      <link>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/more-svi-initial-guesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2014 14:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chasethedevil.github.io/post/more-svi-initial-guesses/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I showed one could extract the SVI parameters from a best fit parabola at-the-money. It seemed to work reasonably well, but I found some real market data where it can be much less satisfying.

Sometimes (actually not so rarely) the ATM slope and curvatures can&amp;rsquo;t be matched given rho and b found through the asymptotes. As a result if I force to just match the curvature and set m=0 (when the slope can&amp;rsquo;t be matched), the simple ATM parabolic guess looks shifted. <a href="/post/more-svi-initial-guesses/">Read More…</a> <p>Copyright 2006-2016 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
