<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misc on Chase the Devil</title>
    <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in misc on Chase the Devil</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2006-2018 Fabien Le Floc&#39;h. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 07:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://chasethedevil.github.io/tags/misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Covid-19 Fake News</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/covid19-fake-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/covid19-fake-news/</guid>
      <description>One thing that motivated me for vaccination is the fake news propaganda against the Covid-19 vaccines.&#xA;A mild example relates to the data from Israel about the delta variant. This kind of article, with the title &amp;ldquo;Covid 19 Case Data in Israel, a Troubling Trend&amp;rdquo;, puts emphasis on the doubts on the effectivness of the vaccine:&#xA;the vaccine appears to have a negligible effect on an individual as to whether he/she catches the current strain.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are traditional banks ready for the 21st century?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/are-tradional-banks-ready-for-the-21st/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/are-tradional-banks-ready-for-the-21st/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow up on my parents phishing scam.&#xA;After several weeks, my parents and I were finally able to have a real world meeting with the advisor at the bank. The advisor is a young woman with an obvious background in sales.&#xA;In order to process the paperwork around the reimbursement of the phishing scam, the main issue was the request of the original phishing e-mail by the bank, as my mother had deleted the e-mail.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yesterday, Pirates Took Over My Parents Bank Account</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/yesterday-pirates-took-over-my-parents-bank-account/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 07:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/yesterday-pirates-took-over-my-parents-bank-account/</guid>
      <description>This is the story of their hack.&#xA;Yesterday evening, I received a call from my mother, frantic over the phone. She says she sees alerts of withdrawals from her bank account on her phone, with new alerts every 5 minutes or so. I try to ask her if she clicked recently on some e-mail related to her bank. She is so panicked that I don&amp;rsquo;t manage to have an answer. While trying to understand if those alerts are real or not, my wife suggests immediately that my mother should call her bank.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benham disc in web canvas</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/benham_disc_in_web_canvas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 23:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/benham_disc_in_web_canvas/</guid>
      <description>Around 15 years ago, I wrote a small Java applet to try and show the Benham disk effect. Even back then applets were already passé and Flash would have been more appropriate. These days, no browser support Java applets anymore, and very few web users have Java installed. Flash also mostly disappeared. The web canvas is today&amp;rsquo;s standard allowing to embbed animations in a web page. This effect shows color perception from a succession of black and white pictures.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Tufte overrated?</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/is_tufte_overrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 16:11:30 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/is_tufte_overrated/</guid>
      <description>Tufte proposes interesting guidelines to present data, or even to design written semi-scientific papers or books. Some advices are particularly relevant like the careful use of colors (don&amp;rsquo;t use all the colors of the rainbow just because you can), and in general don&amp;rsquo;t add lines in a graph or designs that are not directly relevant to the message that needs to be conveyed. There is also a parallel with Feynman message against (Nasa) Powerpoint presentations.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moved to hugo</title>
      <link>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/moved-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 21:00:57 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chasethedevil.github.io/post/moved-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>I moved my blog from blogger to Hugo. Blogger really did not evolve since Google take-over in 2003. Wordpress is today much nicer and prettier. It&amp;rsquo;s clear that Google did not invest at all, possibly because blogs are passé. Compared to mid 2000, there are very few blogs today. Even programming blogs are scarce. It could be interesting to quantify this. My theory is that it is the direct consequence of the popularity of social networks, and especially facebook (possibly also stackoverflow for programmers): people don&amp;rsquo;t have time anymore to write as their extra-time is used on social networks.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
